<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An essay on the coin and commerce of the kingdom trade and treasure (which are twins) being the only supporters thereof next to religion and justice.</title>
            <author>Praed, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3163A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221798</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833055</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833055</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37530</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55623)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37530)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2053:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An essay on the coin and commerce of the kingdom trade and treasure (which are twins) being the only supporters thereof next to religion and justice.</title>
                  <author>Praed, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed and published for the consideration of the present and future sessions of Parliament,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous. By John Praed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Coinage --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commercial policy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37530:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY ON THE Coin and Commerce OF THE KINGDOM, <hi>Trade and Treaſure</hi> (Which are Twins) Being the only SUPPORTERS thereof NEXT TO Religion and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Merchandize of it is better than the Merchandize of Silver, and the Gain thereof than fine Gold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and Publiſhed for the Conſideration of the Preſent and Future Seſſions of Parliament, 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:37530:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37530:2"/>
            <head>To the High Court of Parliament, and particularly to the Grand Committee of Trade appointed <hi>(Mart. 19 Feb. 94.)</hi> to ſit every <hi>Tueſday, Thurſday,</hi> and <hi>Saturday,</hi> in the Afternoon; and to the Honourable Committee appointed to receive Propoſals for prevention of <hi>Clipping</hi> and <hi>Coining.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce I expoſe the following Particulars for the Publick Good, and do moſt humbly ſubmit them to your Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Protection, I hope no particular Perſon will be diſpleaſed with me for relating only what ſome others think fit to ſay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37530:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>PART I.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>SOmetimes before the late Revolution I have heard the <hi>S AVH</hi> of ſome other Countries compare the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in many parallel reſpects to the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Greeks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Two Nations very honourable and brave in their Anceſtry, but Ignoble and Baſe in the Degeneracy of their Deſcendants, for which they now both ſuffer, both under a Heathen and a Chriſtian Yoke, from which <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And it ſhould be the oftner in our Litany, becauſe the Wiſe <hi>Venetians</hi> (more worthily than the others) do value themſelves on a proſpect of futurity at a very great diſtance, and will never (in their Senate) enact any thing as to day, until they conſider, and ſee what will come of it to morrow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>The Form and State of the Jewiſh Government was often chang'd, its Luſtre obſcured, and its Puiſſance and Grandeur leſſen'd and impair'd according to the Degrees of the People's Tranſgreſſions.</p>
                  <p>Who <hi>drew Iniquity with Cords of Vanity, and ſinned as it were with a Cart-rope.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For which <hi>their Silver was turned into Droſs, and their Juſtice into Wormwood; their Cities were burned with Fire, their Lands Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers devoured it in their preſence, the People were oppreſſed every one by another, and the rewards of their own hands were given them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And at laſt they were entirely left without a Sceptre, and brought under the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoke, as our Religion had lately been, had not the Providence of God protected it by means of his Heroick and moſt Excellent Majeſty, and his late moſt religious and Royal Conſort of Famous and Everlaſting Memory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37530:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>And as the <hi>Jews</hi> were, ſo were the <hi>Greeks,</hi> who became firſt ſo careleſs of their Honour, and afterwards of their Countrey's, (minding at laſt only their private) Intereſt, that when they loſt <hi>Coiro Docaſtron</hi> they laugh'd at it, and ſlightingly ſaid (by way of Preface and Introduction to their future Misfortune and Diſtreſs) That it <hi>ſignify'd but</hi> (as the words do) <hi>a Pig-ſtye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſoon after the <hi>Turks</hi> taught them by woful Experience, to underſtand what it is not to underſtand and redreſs Grievances in their prime, before they come to an irreparable paſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>The great <hi>Grievances</hi> which now we all complain of (and not a little but much too late) are <hi>our Clipp'd Silver and Droſs-money, and our decay of Treaſure and Trade together.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſince four ſuch ſad Calamities have befallen this Kingdom in ſuch a time of War, let us firſt enquire into the Cauſes of them, <hi>the knowledge of the Cauſe being the firſt ſtep to the Care.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the general Cauſe of ſo general a Calamity (not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unlike that of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Greeks,</hi> both in Cauſe and Effect) muſt needs be firſt our general Degeneracy, and our little regard to <hi>Religion, Grievances, Trade and Juſtice,</hi> for which there are appointed four principal Committees at the opening of every Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Parliament.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">And here it may be noted that the <hi>Dutch,</hi> &amp;c. have of late Years exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted both Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Goods from us, and have <hi>paid us</hi> for both but <hi>in our own Coin,</hi> I mean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Money as they Coined and Clipped for ſuch kind of Commerce.</note> A particular (and a very conſiderable) Cauſe of the decay of our Treaſure in general (I mean of our Money and Manufacture) is <hi>the Over balance of Trade,</hi> which the greateſt part of the Wiſer World have long ſince gained from us, and whereby they have exhauſted our Treaſure, either in Bills, Money, Bullyon or Goods, which (as ſome of them eſpecially have managed the Matter) hath been almoſt equal gain to them, and the like loſs to us.</p>
                  <p>For if (for inſtance) we import one Year with another, Goods to the value of Three Millions Sterling, and do export Goods but to the value of Two Millions, the Nation muſt yearly loſe a Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion one way or another, and will be in the ſame State and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37530:4"/>Condition of a Gentlemen, that ſpends Fifteen hundred Pounds a Year out of a Thouſand Pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> if Matters be not remedied.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Edward</hi> the Third's time the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had the Over-balance of Trade in their favour; and that King having prohibited the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of our Wool, ordained new Coin for Conveniency, &amp;c. having the Advantage of War by that Advantage of Trade; and having many Voluntiers (for Men's Courage ſympathize with their Coin as it is baſe or noble) invaded <hi>France</hi> with a Valiant and Victorious Army, and was the firſt King that Quarter'd the Arms of <hi>France</hi> with thoſe of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>England,</hi> under Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> had likewiſe great Advantages in War with <hi>Spain,</hi> &amp;c. by means of the Advantage it then alſo had in Trade, as well as it hath by Nature and Situation.</p>
                  <p>But in the four latter Reigns which ſucceeded hers, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded his preſent Majeſty's, (<hi>in a ſlothful and drowſie Peace</hi> as my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> calls it in his <hi>Advancement of Learning</hi>) the Princes and their People (like one another) neglecting firſt the Reformed Religion, next the Juſtice, then the Trade, and at laſt the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Nation (as well as the State of War which Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> left it in) did loſe in general not only their Courage, but ſo much of their Coin and other Treaſure, as would <hi>non-plus</hi> the Arithmetick of <hi>Archimedes</hi> (who undertook to write the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Sands) to caſt up an Account thereof.</p>
                  <p>For the moſt modeſt Computations do reckon (from Matters of the moſt Infallible Fact,) that from the Firſt of King. <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, to the laſt of King <hi>James</hi> the Second, this Nation loſt one Year with another above Two Millions Sterling, by Trading only with two or three other Nations, on unequal, and diſadvantageous Terms.</p>
                  <p>And King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second was made ſo ſenſible (by Mr. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey</hi> and others) of the vaſt Advantage which the <hi>French</hi> then had of us by our ſo diſadvantageous Trading with them in particular, that he promiſed the Nation a <hi>Council of Trade conſiſting of ſome of the Principal Merchants of each Company, of ſome of the beſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified Gentlemen in the Kingdom; and for the greater Honour thereof, ſome of His Majeſties own Privy Council;</hi> but <hi>he promiſed like a Merchant,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And if One hundred Pounds,<note place="margin">As Sir <hi>Joſiah Child</hi> caſts it up in his New Diſcourſe of Trade, <hi>p. 9.</hi>
                     </note> laid out for Seventy Years at Ten <hi>per Cent per Annum,</hi> Intereſt upon Intereſt, will, in that time, gain One hundred Two thouſand Four hundred Pounds, what muſt this Nation have loſt if we reckon only by the Two Millions <hi>per Annum</hi> aforeſaid?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37530:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>Another particular Cauſe of the decay of our Treaſure, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with our Trade, is our own Exportations of Money inſtead of Goods; becauſe Money (as it is, and may be, carried out) pays little or no Freight from hence, and no Cuſtom at all abroad, whereas it's otherwiſe on Goods.</p>
                  <p>For the greater Policy of other Countries have raiſed their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions on our Goods, to encourage our ſending them Bills or Money for their Manufactures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to prevent the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our own, which will be our Ruine, if we are not more, and more aware of it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe the leſs our People apply themſelves to Manufacture, the more they will follow ſuch Cheats, as Clipping and Coining, or ſuch Profellions as are deſtructive to the Eſtates, Bodies, and Souls of any People, unleſs they are executed with all honeſt Art, and Science.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe we have nothing in return for our Goods, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Money (for our Bad they will not take) but conſumptive Commodities, unleſs they recoin our good Money (as they often do) into ſuch bad Coin (as moſt of our bad Money now is,) and convey it us again, not only Clipp'd, but Cropp'd home, almoſt to the Ears of its Image; and yet they have, either Goods for ſuch Money, or better Money, or Bills of Exchange.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>Another Cauſe of our Money, (eſpecially our Mill'd Money,) being Tranſported into other Countries, and Melted down into Plate in our own, is, becauſe every Crown was worth Six Pence more than it went for, when it ſhould rather have been worth ſo much leſs, ſo that for want of Honeſty in the Clippers, and Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the Coiners, <hi>the Rewards of our own Hands have been given unto us,</hi> as it was unto the <hi>Jews,</hi> when <hi>their Silver was turned into Droſs, and their Juſtice into Wormwood.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>Another Cauſe of our want of good Coin,<note place="margin">Cottoni Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huma, <hi>p.</hi> 300.</note> I take (from Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Cotton</hi>) to be, for that all the Currant Silver hath been Cull'd by ſome Goldſiniths, and turned into Bullyon, or Tranſported; which ill Patriot Goldſmiths, and others, have formerly more endamag'd the State by Culling, than any others by<note n="*" place="margin">For Clipping was not ſo much in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion as 'tis now.</note> Clipping.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:37530:5"/>
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>And the Cauſe that the Mint remains unfurniſhed,<note place="margin">Ditto. P. 301.</note> is the Charge of Coinage raiſed in price ſo far above all other Places, conſtraining each Man to carry his Bullyon, where he may receive, by Coinage, the leſs of Loſs. And therefore, if it may pleaſe his Majeſty, to reduce the Prizes here, to the Rates of other of our Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Countries, there will be no doubt but the Mint will beat, as heretofore.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>And there is another Cauſe of the Exportation of our Coin;<note place="margin">Ditto. P. 301.</note> and that is, <hi>The vaſt Summs of Money, which the neceſſary Occaſions of War calls from his Majeſty, to the Parts beyond the Seas, where we have leaſt of Commodities to make even the Ballance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the War is (as it hath been, and may be, more and more, prov'd to be) of greater Advantage, to ſuch an extravagant People as we are, than Peace; for the <hi>French, Dutch,</hi> and others, do deal with us in time of Peace; and (indeed, as ſometimes we deal with them, in time of War) by Means of our Wool, Tin, Lead, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the Fowler dealt with the Eagle, when he feather'd his Shaft with her own Quill.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:37530:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>PART II.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>HAving enquired into ſome of the Cauſes of our decay of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, we are here to conſider of ſome ways and means to remedy the Effects. And ſince the Mamers of Men do ſo ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize with their Money: In the firſt place,
<q>
                        <l>Taught by our Loſs, let us the Cauſe reverſe,</l>
                        <l>And mend thoſe Manners that produc'd the Curſe.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Walſh</hi> on the Death of the Queen.</note>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>In the next place we muſt neceſſarily think of reminting all our Money, both New, and Old, Weighty, and Light, whatever it coſts us, and make it of no leſs, nor more value than it muſt go for.</p>
                  <p>For if our good Money be worth more than it goes for, it will be exported from us to other Countries, and we ſhall have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from them for it, but New Clipp'd and Droſs-money, ſuch as now paſſeth Currant amongſt us, or elſe Exceſſive, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive Commodities.</p>
                  <p>And if our Money is worth much leſs, than it goes for (as now ſome Half Crowns, that go for Thirty, are ſcarce worth Ten Pence, and ſome are intrinſically worth nothing) other Countries will (as they do) Coin, and Import it upon us to our Ruine, as aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>For they will not import ſuch bad Money, but they will have good Money for it, if any is going; if not, Bills, or Goods, which they may have from us, as well as we can have them from one another, for the like Money. And then what Looſers and Gainers we, and they, muſt be, from the firſt to the laſt, any Man (that has Common Sence) may very eaſily imagine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:37530:6"/>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>And, in the next place, there muſt be means found out to raiſe ſuch a Fund, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as will encourage the bringing in of Bullion and Plate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>Now the Over-Balance of Trade (which hath exhauſted abundance of our Treaſure) would naturally bring in Bullion and Plate, as it did of late Years to the <hi>French,</hi> to their great Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in the late Wars.</p>
                  <p>And it hath been made ſufficiently manifeſt, that we have more Materials for Manufacture, and, by confequence, for getting the Over-Balance of Trade, than any other Nation in the World; and only want People for Encouragement, and Encouragement for People to contrive (as the <hi>French</hi> did) <hi>as many various things as poſſible, for Exportation; which is the Life of Home-Trade, and Navigation, and the main means to bring in Money.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>And the better to raiſe Money, for this Fund, within, as well as from without,<note place="margin">True Engliſh Intereſt, <hi>P. 8.</hi>
                     </note> the Kingdom, <hi>we ſhould enjoin our own People chiefly to uſe our own Manufactures; and make them pay treble Cuſtom that bring in any Foreign Manufacture, that we do make, or may make, at home.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Home-Trade being our Primary Advantage, and Foreign Trade but a Secondary Help; and the greater our Exportations are, for the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Country, the greater will our Importation be, for the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the King,</hi> &amp;c. (For Goods muſt be paid for, by Goods, or Money.) We ſhould (to gain the Over-Balance of Trade, and, thereby to bring in other Nations Treaſure) deal with other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as other Nations deal with us; that is, lay greater and greater Impoſitions on ſome of their Commodities, and, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, leſs upon ſome others.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Silk Trade will ſave us vaſt Summs of Money,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ditto P. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>now ſent to</hi> France <hi>and</hi> Italy, <hi>and we make it here better, and cheaper; and then
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37530:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>we ſhould have it to furniſh our ſelves, and our Neighbours, and tranſport abundance to our Southern Plantations, and bring for it Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or ſuch Commodities as we moſt want, or pay ready Money for.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A greater</hi> Impoſition on Foreign Commodities, which come from ſuch Places as have the Over-Balance of Trade in their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, would bring us in, or ſave us, a great deal of Money.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe it would prevent the great Importation of Foreign Commodities, or lower the prices thereof, and, by conſequence prevent the greater Exportation of our Money.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe it would encourage the Importation of ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities from other Countries, that take more of our Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities from us, as Raiſins from <hi>Spain,</hi> and Currans from <hi>Turkey,</hi> where they have as good, and better; and can have, in a little time, as much, and more than they have at <hi>Zant,</hi> &amp;c. — <hi>The</hi> Turkey, Spaniſh, <hi>the</hi> Guiny, Weſt-India <hi>Trade,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ditto. P. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>are very good to us; but the</hi> Weſt-India <hi>Trade will be the only Advantage to us, if we fix it rightly, which will vend not only our own Commodities, but bring us ſtore of Silver, and Increaſe of Navigation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Becauſe the Places that take ſo little of our Manufacture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from us, cannot impoſe upon us as we may upon them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they do (as they often do) lay the greater Impoſitions on their own Commodities, the more they find us inclin'd or engag'd to them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A People may be undone by ſome kind of Merchandize;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ditto. P. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>for many Merchants, ſo they advantage themſelves, care not what Injury they may do to the Publick; for as they were wont formerly, and do ſtill ſerve thoſe of</hi> Guiny, <hi>to carry them Beads, Looking-Glaſſes, and ſuch like things, and bring away their Gold; ſo they deal often with their own Country-men: For finding us fantaſtical and voluptuous, they tempt us with all ſorts of</hi> French <hi>Toys,</hi> Indy, <hi>and</hi> Japan <hi>Trifles,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which fetch away our Money and ſolid Wealth,</hi> &amp;c. — <hi>But it were well if we could manage the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Trade, as the</hi> Dutch <hi>do, who carry no Silver from</hi> Holland, <hi>but drive the Trade with the Silver they get from</hi> Japan, <hi>in Exchange for other Commodities they bring to them; which we may do in a better, and ſpeedier, way than they can, if permitted by means of the</hi> Weſt-Indies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But as things are now, we are Loſers by moſt of our Trading,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ditto. P. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially our</hi> French, <hi>and</hi> Canary: <hi>We import, as one Author ſaith, of</hi> French <hi>Commodities, as Silks, Laces, Linen, and the like, Sixteen
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37530:7"/>hundred thouſand Pounds a-Year more than we export of our own; and of</hi> Canary <hi>Wine, One hundred and Fifty thouſand Pounds worth more than we export alſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Joſiah Child</hi> in his Book, aforeſaid, <hi>p.</hi> 162. Saith, <hi>The Trade for</hi> Canary <hi>Wines I take to be a moſt pernicious Trade to</hi> England, <hi>becauſe thoſe Iſlands conſume very little of our Manufactures; neither do they furniſh us with any Commodities to be farther Manufactured here: And the Wines we bring from thence are, for the moſt part, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with Ready Money; ſo that ſomething is neceſſary to be done to compel thoſe Iſlanders to ſpend more of our</hi> Engliſh <hi>Commodities, and to ſell their Wares cheaper, which every Year they advance in Price, or elſe to leſſen the Conſumption of them in</hi> England.</p>
                  <p>And, <hi>p.</hi> 161. he ſaith "<hi>The</hi> Venetians <hi>being a People that take from us very little of our Manufactures, have prohibited our</hi> Engliſh <hi>Cloth, and from whoſe Territories we receive great Quantities of Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, purchaſed with our Ready Money: It ſeems to me advantageous for</hi> England, <hi>that that Importation ſhould be diſcouraged,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I have too great an Honour and Regard for His Majeſty's Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, than to ſpeak of prohibiting thoſe Commodities: But a greater Impoſition on them here, would oblige the firſt Owners thereof to take Commodities for Commodities, and to leſſen the Prices,<note place="margin">☞</note> and the Impoſitions, in the Places of their growth: The Duke of <hi>Venice</hi> having 12 Dollars a thouſand, as the King of <hi>England</hi> hath 14 Shillings a-hundred Cuſtom on the Currans.</p>
                  <p>And thoſe Impoſitions, together with the firſt Coſt, and all other Charges, being to be paid at laſt by thoſe only who will be pleaſed to eat Currans, a farther Impoſition on them for the Reaſons aforeſaid, can be very diſpleaſing to no particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And the Publick cannot think any Ill of it; eſpecially ſince his Majeſty hath ſo often recommended to his Parliament <hi>the Balance, Regulation, and Advancement of Trade:</hi> And ſince the <hi>Venetians</hi> will often boaſt that they have had above Forty Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions Sterling in Money, by Bills, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for their <hi>Merda,</hi> as they ſometimes take occaſion enough to call their Currans, without the Common Civility of <hi>Sir Reverence.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>All manner of Encouragement to the honeſt Exporting Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, and to the moſt Induſtrious and moſt Ingenious Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facturers, of what Nation ſoever, would bring us in much Money, and People. For much People create much Community; much
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37530:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Community, much Commerce; much Commerce, much Induſtry; much Induſtry, much Ingenuity; much Ingenuity, much Arts; much Arts, much Manufacture; much Manufacture, much Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick Trade; much Domeſtick Trade, by means of Exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, introduceth much Foreign Money; and much Money, and many People, improve both the Value and Price of Land.</p>
                  <p>And as it would improve our Wealth, and the Revenues of all Ranks of Men, ſo it would prevent the Exportation of our Wool better than any Laws that can be executed here in <hi>England,</hi> whatever might be done in <hi>France,</hi> or elſewhere; by which means we ſhould not loſe, but gain, thoſe Advantages, which the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> have had (of us, and others) by making Cloth of our Wool, as they made <hi>Light</hi> of our <hi>Weighty</hi> Money, and ſent it us again for other Money or Goods.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>An eſteemable Encouragement to all Men and Women,<note place="margin">A great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample would be an Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement good and eſteema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enough.</note> that would <hi>wear</hi> Cloth, and Stuff, all the Winter; and a general burying in Woollen, would ſave us ſo much Money as would go a great way towards the Fund; and a Peny ſav'd being of more value than a Peny got, it would advantage us more ways than one.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the more we conſume of Foreign Commodities,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">True <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt, <hi>p.</hi> 47.</note> 
                     <hi>the more we ſtrengthen Foreigners, and weaken our ſelves, without we over balance it by our own Exportation; for if we have not Manufactures, and Home-Productions, had we never ſo many Silver Mines, they would be exhauſted, as we have an Example in the</hi> Spaniard, <hi>who conſumes all the Silver he hath from the</hi> Indies, <hi>on Foreign Things he hath occaſion for.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>An Impoſition on all the Wearers of <hi>Silk, Silver,</hi> and <hi>Gold,</hi> would bring in Money for the Fund, or encourage the Woollen Manufacture, or both; and the leſs Gold and Silver is worn (as well as Foreign Silks) the leſs will fall to the ground, and be loſs to the Nation.</p>
                  <p>But I believe the more our People were confined to Cloth and Stuff, the more Silk, Silver, and Gold they would <hi>wear</hi> — If <hi>Shimei,</hi> when he was confined to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> had the greater mind to go to <hi>Gath;</hi> if he had been confined to <hi>Gath,</hi> he would have had a greater mind to go to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:37530:8"/>And we are obſerved to drink more Wine, now it is raiſed to Eighteen Pence the Quart, and Two Shillings the Bottle, by Act of the Vintners, than when we were more confin'd to Six Pence a-Quart by Act of Parliament.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>An Impoſition upon all prohibited Goods: It being no impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy to take off the Prohibition, ſince it prevents not the Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, which has been very prejudicial to the Nation in general, whatever it hath been to particular Perſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>An Imporſition on all Foreign Lace Imported, and on all our Wearers thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">The more Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Men paid upon this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, themore it would be for their Honour; and the leſs they paid, the better huſbands they would be, both for themſelves and their Country. For the leſs Silver would liedead, and the more Coin would be Currant in the Kingdom, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the value of Lands, and the promotion of Manufacture, and the more Agriculture and Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture do flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Nation is from fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note> An Impoſition upon all ſuch, as ſerve themſelves in Private, and Publick Houſes in Plate; and the more upon Publick Houſes, becauſe they may bring in their Plate, at ſo much on Ounce, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the re-minting the Money, or to have New Money for it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>An Impoſition on the <hi>Money-Changers,</hi> they having been Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pals to the Clippers, as much as <hi>Demetrius</hi> was to <hi>Diana's Silver Smiths.</hi> And had their Tables been over thrown by our Juſtice, as the Money-Changers were by Jeſus, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. When the Jews Silver was turning into Droſs, the Den of thoſe Thieves had not done us ſo much Miſchief.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="section">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>A different Impoſition of ſo much a-Year upon all Taverns, Inns, Coffee-Houſes, Ale-Houſes, Brew-Houſes and Bake-Houſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="section">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>An Impoſition by way of Fine and Licenſe, on all thoſe that at firſt enter upon thoſe Profeſſions that are unprofitable (or rather
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37530:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>deſtructive) to the Nation, which would put our Folk the more upon Manufacture.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="section">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>An Impoſition on all dilatory Defendants in Law and Equity that (<hi>by ſtaving and Tailing with Writs of Error, Reverſe of judgment and Demurrer</hi>) have plagued the Plaintiffs above a Year and a Day; which is as long as any Suit ſhould laſt in Law, or in Equity. And the more Years they have delayed our Juſtice, and made it <hi>a true and conſtant Friend to all that regularly offend,</hi> the more and more Impoſitions ſhould be laid upon them, and upon ſome others, which (I humbly think, as I am an honeſt Subject) is more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and ſeaſonable than</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="section">
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <head type="sub">For Letters of Favours;</head>
                  <p>Either for mitigation, or for diſpatch of Juſtice.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cottoni Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huma,</hi> p. <hi>193.</hi> Of Manner and Means, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of the firſt ſort, there be many found in <hi>Henry</hi> VI. and <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> IV's time, ſometimes of Protection, ſometimes freeing Men from Arreſts, by calling them up to appear before the King's Council. Sometimes in Caſes highly Criminal, relieving the Priſoner, in commanding the Judges to make ſtay of all Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, upon ſuppoſal of indirect Practices, until the King was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter informed.</p>
                  <p>Of the ſecond ſort, there are many in <hi>Henry</hi> VII's time, where the King hath taken Money for writing to the Judges of Aſſize his Letters of Favour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="section">
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <head type="sub">For maintenance of Religion, and the Church.<note place="margin">P. 172.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>As in the Year 1166. to <hi>Henry</hi> II. was given 12 <hi>d.</hi> in the Pound; and the 18 <hi>Edward</hi> 1. a Fifteenth was granted to expel the <hi>Jews.</hi> And <hi>Anno</hi> 4 <hi>Richard</hi> II. a Tenth to the Clergy, and a Fifteeenth to the Commons, for his help, to ſuppreſs the <hi>Wicklivian</hi> Hereſie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="section">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:37530:9"/>
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <p>For Support of the Laws and the Liberties of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Wealth.<note place="margin">P. 173.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>For Redreſs of Aggrievances.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="section">
                  <head>XXI.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Particular Grants of the Subject, by Loan, Compulſive.<note place="margin">P. 177.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>So were the Merchants of <hi>Florence, Venice,</hi> and <hi>Luka,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by an Order in Council, 3 <hi>Hen</hi> III. becauſe they had <hi>grace &amp; ſufferance du Roy Graunts priviledges &amp; reportants grand lucre pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Exerciſe de leur Merchandre en le Angliterre.</hi> And the Perſons that refuſed to lend, were committed to the Fleet; neither were the <hi>Engliſh</hi> more free, in <hi>Anno</hi> 30 <hi>Henry</hi> VI. divers being enjoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to attend the Council-Table, or elſe to pay the demanded Loan.</p>
                  <p>In the time of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. <hi>Anno</hi> 14 of his Reign, he exacted by way of Loan Ten pounds in the hundred on all Goods, Jewels, Utenſils, and Land, and according to the extremeſt rate revealed by Oath of the Poſſeſſors; notwithſtanding there is a Law, 2 <hi>Richard</hi> II. that none ſhall be denied in demand of any Loan his reaſonable Excuſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="section">
                  <head>XXII.</head>
                  <p>Kings raiſe Money,<note place="margin">P. 184.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. By Trading themſelves.</p>
                  <p>Thus did <hi>Edward</hi> I. <hi>Anno</hi> 22. ſeize into his Hands all the Wool in the Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus did <hi>Edward</hi> III. <hi>Anno</hi> 12. with all the Tin.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="section">
                  <head>XXIII.</head>
                  <p>Kings raiſe Money,<note place="margin">P. 185.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>By Licenſing others to Trade in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities ———— Lawful or Unlawful.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Lawfully but ſolely.</p>
                  <p>Thus did <hi>Henry</hi> VI. by Approbation of Parliament, with all the Trade of Allom, for Two Years granted to the Merchants
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37530:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>Southampton,</hi> for 8000 <hi>l.</hi> and again for the like Sum to thoſe of <hi>Genoa.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Unlawful or prohibited.</p>
                  <p>Thus did many of the Kings, &amp;c.<note place="margin">P. 186.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>To divers Citizens of <hi>Londin, Henry</hi> IV. diſpenſed for great Quantities of Tin for Seven Years, paying 400 <hi>l.</hi> Yearly above the uſual Cuſtom.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="section">
                  <head>XXIV.</head>
                  <p>Kings raiſe Money.<note place="margin">P. 187.</note>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <label>By</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Farming out of Ships.</item>
                           <item>2. Raiſing the Book of Rates.</item>
                           <item>3. Farming the Cuſtoms.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Farming of Ships</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the Merchants, and taking ſecurity of them, either to bring in, or carry out, Yearly as much Commodities as ſhall yield the King in Cuſtoms on, or elſe to make it up out of their own Money.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Raiſing the Book of Rates.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This was in ſome ſort done <hi>Conſenſu Mercatorum,</hi> by <hi>Edward</hi> I. and <hi>Edward</hi> III. and again in <hi>Henry</hi> VIII's time;<note place="margin">lindx;</note> of which the Houſe of <hi>Burgundy</hi> complained,<note place="margin">But we ſeldom complain of the breach of our Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Treaties of Commerce in other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</note> as againſt the Treaty of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
                  <p>The like did <hi>Edward</hi> III. <hi>Anno</hi> 1. Confirming <hi>Anno</hi> 2. the great Charter for Free Traffick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thus it continued all his Reign, being a time of great Neceſſity and Expence, by reaſon of his Wars, he ſometimes taking an Advantage, either to raiſe an Impoſition, or elſe to gain Aid from the People in diſcharge thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="section">
                  <head>XXV.</head>
                  <p>Kings raiſe Money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 191.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>By Liberties.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 193.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this was one of the uſualleſt and eaſieſt means to raiſe Money from the People, becauſe it lighteth only upon the beſt Abilities. And if there were now but 20 <hi>l.</hi> taken of every Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration; of every Perſon that hold by Charter his Liberties, 5 <hi>l.</hi> for renewing them; and of every one, that claimeth by Preſcription, 10 <hi>l.</hi> for Purchaſe of a Charter: All which would be eaſie, and acceptable; it would amount to above 100000 <hi>l.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="section">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:37530:10"/>
                  <head>XXVI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Honours.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 195.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that either by Power Legal, or Election.</p>
                  <p>Of the firſt, it is only in reſpect of Land, whereby every Man is to fine when the King ſhall require, that hath Ability to be made a Knight, and is not: Of this ſort there be plentiful Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
                  <p>The other out of Choice and Grace, as <hi>Hugo de Putiaco,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> was by King <hi>Richard</hi> 1. created Earl of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton,</hi> for a great Summ of Money. And I doubt not but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe times would ſet their Ambition at as high a price. And for his Majeſty now to make a degree of Honour Hereditary, as Baronets, next Under-Barons, and grant them in Tail, taking of every one 1000 <hi>l.</hi> in Fine, it would raiſe with eaſe 100000 <hi>l.</hi> and, by a judicious Election, be a means to content thoſe worthy Perſons in the Common-Wealth, that by the confuſed admiſſion of many Knights of the Bath, held themſelves all this time diſgraced.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="section">
                  <head>XXVII.</head>
                  <p>Kings raiſe Money by Offices.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">But if Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſhould be ſold now, we ſhould pay dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer for it than we do: And, God knows, there are Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions on Juſtice enough already.</note> Thus did King <hi>John</hi> with the Chancellorſhip, ſelling it for time of Life to <hi>Grey,</hi> for 5000 Marks.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>France,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aemyliusin vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, <hi>Lew.</hi> 12.</note> 
                     <hi>Lewis</hi> XII. called the Father of his Country, did ſo with all Offices, not being of <hi>Judicature,</hi> which his Succeſſors did not forbear.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Spain</hi> it is uſual;<note place="margin">Vaſq. Cap. 40. Ex Inſtruct. Car. 5. ad Phil. 2.</note> and <hi>Vaſque,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Advocate defendeth the Lawfulneſs of it.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Charles</hi> V. preſcribeth it to his Son, as a Rule in his laſt Inſtruction, drawing his ground of Reaſon and Conveniency from the Example and Practice of the See of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the like might be of all inferiour Promotions, whether Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical or Temporal, and it would honeſtly raiſe a great deal of Money.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="section">
                  <head>XXVIII.</head>
                  <p>Taxes were better raiſed any way,<note place="margin">☞</note> than from the Land;<note place="margin">True Engliſh Intereſt, <hi>p. 68.69,</hi> &amp;c.</note> for that drives the Money out of the Country, which ſeldom returns,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37530:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>and is hard to be got to it upon any occaſion; but it would be great advantage to his Majeſty, and gratifie his Subjects Infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if he could get a conſiderable Revenue ſomewhere from without.</p>
                  <p>By which means his own People might be eaſed at home, which would bind them to him eternally; beſides the great Advantage it would be to the Nation, by ſuch a Yearly income of Silver continually.</p>
                  <p>And queſtionleſs the King of <hi>England</hi> might have five times the Revenue he hath, brought Yearly to him from the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> when he pleaſes; beſides the vaſt Trade, which would enſue by it, to all his Subjects.</p>
                  <p>However there might be ways found out, that no Taxes might ever be laid on the ſubſtantial part of the Nation, Country, or City, Land, or Houſes; but only on the Vices of the People, as in all Taverns, Ale-houſes, Foreign needleſs Commodities, and on debauch'd Perſons.</p>
                  <p>And alſo double Cuſtoms on all ſuch Goods, brought over, that we might make here, as Silk, Linen, Tapeſtry, Lace, Gloves, Ribbons, Paper, and many things more.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="section">
                  <head>XXIX.</head>
                  <p>And (<hi>to get a conſiderable Revenue from without</hi>) a Treble Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition on all our Conſuls, and Factors reſiding in Foreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. An Impoſition of ſo much <hi>per Cent</hi> on every <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſul and Factor, according to his Perſonal Eſtate and Yearly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, they having paid nothing towards the War, nor do they pay any thing in time of Peace.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. An Impoſition of ſo much <hi>per Cent</hi> upon all Commodities, as they ſhall ſend to <hi>England</hi> for their own Accompt; becauſe the more they ſend, the leſs will be the Gains of our Domeſtick Merchants, who pay all Rates and Taxes, when the Factors pay neither, tho' their Advantage of fore-ſtalling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable to our Merchants, and ruinous to the Kingdom.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. An Impoſition (after the Property is alter'd) upon all Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Commodities, to be laden by any <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or Alien Factors, for any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man's Account, for <hi>England,</hi> or any other Nation; which Impoſition (being Foreign) would be felt neither by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, by the Merchant, nor by any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man; and it would be both for the Intereſt, and the Honour of the Nation.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37530:11"/>I. Becauſe it would naturally lower the Foreign Impoſitions more, than if it had been a Domeſtick Tax; which Foreign Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions are moſt commonly laid on the <hi>Engliſh, by conſent of our Conſuls and Factors,</hi> they being to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants much as Lawyers and Sollicitors are to their Clients. And the other reaſon, why the Alien Impoſitions are ſo much greater than ours on Exportation, is, becauſe we are naturally (to our unnatural ſhame be it ſpoken) more inclined to Alien Commodities, than Aliens are to ours; though ours are, and may be, ſo much better than theirs.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. Becauſe this Impoſition would naturally lower the Price of Foreign Commodities more, than if it had been a Domeſtick Tax. Which Price is, moſt commonly, higher or lower, the more our Conſuls and Factors do agree, or diſagree, to make it ſo. I have known (and ſhall prove it) that our Conſuls, and Factors, have paid three times dearer for Foreign Commodities for our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants than they might have bought them for. And the more they pay, the more they (and the Aliens with whom they combine) do get, and ſo much the more this Nation, in general, loſeth. But a general Loſs is little felt, heard, or underſtood by particular Perſons.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. This Impoſition on the Conſuls, and Factors, would be little felt by them, becauſe the Merchants, moſt commonly, pay them before they pay for their Commodities; or if they do not, it is but ſo much Money laid out, which they are to be re-paid again with Interſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">IV. It would be little felt by the Merchants, becauſe they pay (in a great meaſure tho' not ſo great as it ſhould be) for what they import by the product of their Exportations; which they buy here at Twelve and Eighteen Month's time. And becauſe they are come now almoſt to care not what they pay for foreign Commodities, ſo long as they can have Credit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from their Factors abroad, who make them (or rather their Nation) pay ſoundly for it, and can be re-imburs'd by their Chapmen at home; which is the reaſon that Foreign Commodities have, of later Years ſo riſen to the ruining of this Nation.</p>
                  <p>When I lived abroad, I thought my ſelf (as I was) obliged, by Oath and Indentures, <hi>neither to defraud my Maſter my ſelf, nor to ſuffer any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther body ſo to do, without informing my ſaid Maſter;</hi> and as I did to him, ſo did I to all my other Friends. But when I had ſuffer'd all that Malice could inflict upon me, together with the loſs of my For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and the Lives of Two or Three Men, becauſe I would not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37530:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>combine with our Conſul, and Factors, and their Confederates, to cheat my Country, and my Friends: One of thoſe Friends ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kindly wrote me, that <hi>he would not have me trouble my ſelf, and others, ſo much for them, becauſe the dearer they paid abroad, the dearer they ſold at home,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. Becauſe our Countrey, in general, will feel this Impoſition abroad leſs, than if it had been laid at home by any means what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; and it will be but a little <hi>General Exciſe</hi> paid there, and received here, with a great deal of caſe, and without that plague of the <hi>Publicans.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now if any one ſhould think that theſe Impoſitions on our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and on our own Commodities (for ſo they are when the Property is alter'd) in other Countries, would be a diſhonour to our Nation, I may ſay to him, that he is as much miſtaken both in the Honour, and Intereſt of this Nation, as thoſe are, who think it a Credit to the Kingdom to have our Coin out-weigh other Countries; which in reality is as much a Diſcredit to us, as that their Exportations to us (their Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions eſpecially conſider'd) ſhould exceed ours to them.</p>
                  <p>And I would fain know which is the greateſt diſhonour, for us to lay Impoſitions on our own Factors, and Goods there, or to permit Aliens to lay Impoſitions both on the one, and the other, as I ſhall prove they have done, ſometimes from One to Twenty five <hi>per Cent,</hi> beſides what they have made our Factors pay for <hi>Contrabanda;</hi> for which Mr. <hi>Thomas Cordell,</hi> late Factor at <hi>Zans,</hi> paid Ten thouſand Crowns at once to the <hi>Venetians,</hi> tho' his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence was but ſmall; and our late Conſul, Sir <hi>Clement Harbye,</hi> was the Informer of it: And beſides what they have impos'd on our Merchant-Ships, Maſters, and Mariners.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, our Alien Factors, that have been unnaturally, and impoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically employ'd by our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, have got ſuch vaſt Eſtates, as well as Eſteem from them, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Factors, that they will often value themſelves above their Principals; and to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo, two of them (<hi>Celini</hi> and <hi>Morelli</hi>) could lately afford to give above Twenty thouſand Pound Sterling, to be as they now are, <hi>Noble Men of</hi> Venice.</p>
                  <p>And all this Money (and twenty times more) which they, and ſuch others, have gain'd, having been got more from this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in general, than from their reſpective Merchants in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, a double, or treble, Impoſition ſhould be laid on all Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, bought by any Alien Factor, for any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man's Account.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37530:12"/>And the treble Impoſition, aforeſaid upon our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Factors, is the more reaſonable, becauſe it will take off the Taxes which are impos'd upon them, and their Merchants (and, by conſequence, on this Kingdom) in other Countries; and becauſe ſo many of them die in other Nations, and do leave, or ſpend, ſuch Eſtates there, which this Nation never was, nor ever will be the better for.</p>
                  <p>Indeed thoſe are Impoſitions which were never laid by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nation; but the reaſon may be, becauſe no other Nation could, as we can, do it; they having no ſuch Factories here, or any where elſe, as we have in other Countries, becauſe they will not ſpend other Countries Commodities ſo extravagantly, and ſhamefully, as we do.</p>
                  <p>And theſe Impoſitions would let the World ſee better how we do reſent their impoſing upon us, as well as upon their own and our Commodities, to their great Intereſt, and our Diſadvantage; and would put them more, than otherwiſe we can, or do, upon taking our Commodities on the ſame Terms, and after the ſame rate, that we take theirs.</p>
                  <p>And, whether this takes, or not, if his Majeſty's Conſuls abroad ſhould keep an account of all Foreign Exportations for <hi>England,</hi> and ſend it home to the Counſel of Trade, it might do his Majeſty ſome Service; becauſe it would prevent the ſtealing of Cuſtoms, on which there are greater Impoſitions (for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good) in other Countries, than there are in this Kingdom; and why ſhould any Man be ſuffer'd to cheat his King at home, who ſuffers himſelf, and his Country both, to be ſo baſely cheated abroad?</p>
                  <p>And if thoſe Conſuls would likewiſe honeſtly keep the like ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Prices of ſuch Exportations, they would do their Merchants, and Country alſo, the like Service: And I know no reaſon why it ſhould not be acceptable.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="section">
                  <head>XXX.</head>
                  <p>The Revenues of Princes as they differ much in Quantity, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Greatneſs,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>England</hi>'s Treaſure by Foreign Trade, <hi>p. 151.</hi>
                     </note> Riches, and Trade of their reſpective Dominions, ſo likewiſe is there great diverſity uſed in procuring the ſame, according to the Conſtitution of the Countries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some Kings have Cuſtoms, Tolls, and Impoſts upon all Trade to, and from Foreign Countries.</p>
                  <p>Other Princes and States have Cuſtom upon all new Wares tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported from one City to be uſed in any other City, or Place of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37530:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>their own Dominions: Cuſtoms upon every Alienation; or Sale of live Cattel, Lands, Houſes licens'd; Money upon all Victualling Houſes, and Inn keepers, Head-money; Cuſtom upon all the Corn, Wine, Oil, Salt, and the like, which grow, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed in their Dominions.</p>
                  <p>All which ſeem to be a Rabble of Oppreſſions, ſerving to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich thoſe Princes which exact them, and to make the People poor, and miſerable, which endure them; eſpecially in thoſe Countries where theſe Burthens are laid at heavy rates, as Four, Five, Six, and Seven <hi>per Cent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But when all the Circumſtances and Diſtinction of Places are duly conſidered, they will be found not only neceſſary, and lawful to be uſed in ſome States, but alſo in divers reſpects very proſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Common-wealth.</p>
                  <p>For theſe heavy Contributions are not ſo hurtful to the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the People, as they are commonly eſteem'd; for as the Food and Rayment of the Poor is made dear by Exciſe, ſo doth the price of their labour riſe in proportion, whereby the Burthen (if any be) is ſtill upon the Rich, who are either idle, or, at leaſt, work not in this kind; yet have they the uſe, and are the great Conſumer's of the Poor's Labour.</p>
                  <p>Neither do the Rich neglect in their ſeveral Places, and Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, to advance their Endeavours, according to thoſe times which do exhauſt their Means, and Revenues; wherein if they ſhould peradventure fail, and therefore be forced to abate their ſinful Exceſs, what is all this but Happineſs in a Common-wealth, when Virtue, Plenty, and Arts, ſhall thus be advanced all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:37530:13"/>
               <head>PART III.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>WE have now ſeen ſome of the Cauſes of the decay of our Coin, Treaſure, and Trade, which is as inexcuſably ſcandalous, as it is notoriouſly conſumptive to the Common-Wealth in its Effects.</p>
                  <p>We have alſo Collected, and Conſidered, hitherto, ſome Ways, and Means, to raiſe a Fund, or rather Principal, Money, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy this our diſtracting Diſeaſe. And,</p>
                  <p>In a Paper lately Printed, we find theſe <hi>Propoſals humbly offered to prevent all manner of Abuſes by Clipping, Coining, Melting, Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſporting, or otherwiſe debaſing the Coin of this Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Let all the Money, hereafter Coin'd, be Mill'd: And let all Perſons that ſhall Clip, or any ways Counterfeit, or Deface the ſame, be Fin'd Twenty Pounds, and Baniſh'd the Kingdom: And let it be Penal for any Perſon to receive any ſuch Money.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this I Anſwer, That when the Money is Mill'd, there will be no great fear of having it Clipp'd, becauſe it will not paſs then as other Clipp'd Money does now; but it may be ſo cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Counterfeited, that they deſerve worſe than Baniſhment, and Twenty Pounds Fine, that are found guilty of the Fact. And a Severe Penalty would be too hard upon any one that ſhould be deceived therewith.</p>
                  <p>Nothing but exceeding Care and Judgment can prevent their being ſometime deceived. The People abroad have Scales, and Touchſtones, to prevent the receiving of Counterfeit-Money. And before the Jews Silver was turned into Droſs, <hi>Abraham weighed unto</hi> Ephron <hi>the Silver, which he had named in the Audience of the Sons of</hi> Heth, <hi>Four hundred Shekels of Silver, Currant-Money with the Merchants.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:37530:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>2. <hi>To prevent Melting down, Let the Crown-Piece be Coined of the intrinſick Value of Four Shillings and Six Pence only,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And let each Piece paſs Currant for their reſpective Denominations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Nation will quickly be ſenſible of the Advantage of this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle; for our Merchants will never be at the Expence of exporting Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, when it will be a much greater Profit to have it Coined at home.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I Anſwer, in Sir <hi>Robert Cotton</hi>'s Words, That <hi>Money muſt value</hi> in Pecunia quantum in Maſſa.</p>
                  <p>For Silver is a Commodity, as other Wares;<note place="margin">P. 197.</note> and therefore holdeth its Eſtimation, as they do, according to the Goodneſs.</p>
                  <p>And the Lord Treaſurer <hi>Burleigh, Anno</hi> 1561. when the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of State-Council affected an Abaſement of Coin, after a grave deliberation, adviſed the Queen from it, and never would give way to any ſuch Reſolution in his time.</p>
                  <p>For the Revenues of the Crown being commonly in certain Rents, they muſt in true value, howſoever in verbal ſound,<note place="margin">P. 196.</note> be abated to the proportion that the Money ſhall be abaſed.</p>
                  <p>But that Benefit, which truly the King might more make of Bullion than now he doth, is, to erect again <hi>Cambium Regis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 197.</note> his own Exchange.</p>
                  <p>An Office as ancient, as before <hi>Henry</hi> III. and ſo continued un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. the Profit of it being now ingroſſed amongſt a few Goldſmiths, and would yield above 10000 <hi>l.</hi> a-Year, if it were heedfully regarded.</p>
                  <p>And then ſhould the King himſelf keep his Mint in continual Work, and not ſtand at the Devotion of others to ſupply Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion: He ſhould never want Materials, if Two Things were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. To permit all Men, bringing in Bullion, to trade outward the value thereof in Domeſtick Commodities, at an abated Cuſtom.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. To abate the mighty Indraught of Foreign Manufactures, and unneceſſary Wares, that the outward Trade might over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balance the inward; which otherwiſe will, as it hath done, draw on this deſperate Conſumption of the Common Wealth.<note place="margin">P. 198.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which <hi>Anno</hi> 27 <hi>Edward</hi> III. was otherwiſe;<note place="margin">Ex ſcaccar. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rememb. Regis, 27 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</note> for then the <hi>Exitus</hi> exceeded the <hi>Introitus</hi> by far; and in the laſt Times of Queen <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> As in <hi>Anno</hi> 1553.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:37530:14"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Cottoni Poſthuma,</hi> P. <hi>285. &amp;c.</hi> How our ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Coining doth do it, is now too noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly known to all Men.</note> I cannot but aſſuredly conceive that this intended Project of enhanſing the Coin, will trench both into the Honour, the Juſtice, and the Profit of my Royal Maſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">Honour.</note> Ali Eſtates do ſtand <hi>Magis famâ quam vi,</hi> as <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaith of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Wealth, in every Kingdom, is one of the eſſential Marks of their Greatneſs, and that is beſt expreſt in the Meaſure and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their Moneys.</p>
                  <p>Hence was it, that ſo long as the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire (a Pattern of the beſt Government) held up their Glory, and Greatneſs, they ever maintained with little, or no charge, the Standard of their Coin.</p>
                  <p>But after, the looſe Times of <hi>Commodus</hi> had let in Need by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; and ſo that ſhift of changing the Standard, the Majeſty of that Empire fell by degrees.</p>
                  <p>And, as <hi>Vopiſcus</hi> ſaith, the Steps by which that Statee deſcended, were viſibly known moſt by the gradual alteration of their Coin.</p>
                  <p>And there is no ſurer Symptom of a Conſumption in State, than the Corruption of Money.<note place="margin">1286. ☞</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>What Renown is left to the Poſterity of <hi>Edward</hi> I. in amending the Standard,<note place="margin">Edw. <hi>I.</hi>
                     </note> both in Purity, and Weight, from that of elder, and moſt barbarous Times, muſt ſtick, as a Blemiſh, upon Princes that do the contrary.</p>
                  <p>Thus we ſee it was with <hi>Henry</hi> VI. who after he had begun with abating the Meaſure,<note place="margin">Hen. <hi>VI.</hi>
                     </note> he after fell to abating the Matter, and granted Commiſſions to <hi>Miſſenden,</hi> and others, to practiſe Alchimy to ſerve his Mint. The Extremity of the State, in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, felt this Aggrievance, beſides the Diſhonour it laid upon the Perſon of the King.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. had gained as much of Power and Glory abroad,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII.</note> of Love, and Obedience at home, as ever any, he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Shipwrack of all upon this Rock.</p>
                  <p>When his Daughter,<note place="margin">Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                     </note> Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> came to the Crown, ſhe was happy in Council to mend that Error of her Father, and to reduce the Standard to the ancient Parity, and Purity of her Great Grandfather King <hi>Edward</hi> IV.<note place="margin">Edw. <hi>IV.</hi> Juſtice.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>To avoid the Trick of Permutation, Coin was deviſed as a Rate, and Meaſure of Merchandize, and Manufactures; which, if mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, no Man can tell either what he hath, or what he oweth:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37530:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>No Contract can be certain; and ſo all Commerce, both Publick and Private, deſtroyed, and Men again enforced to Permutation with Things not ſubject to Wit or Fraud.</p>
                  <p>In the laſt part, which is the Diſprofit, this enfeebling the Coin will bring both to his Majeſty, and the Common Wealth,<note place="margin">Profit.</note> I muſt diſtinguiſh the Moneys of Gold, and Silver, as they are Bullion, or Commodities, and as they are Meaſure, the one the intrinſick Quality, which is at the King's Pleaſure, as all other Meaſures; the other, the intrinſick Quantity of pure Metal, which is in the Merchant to value, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What the King will ſuffer by it in the Rents of his Lands, is demonſtrated enough by the Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations ſince the 18th. <hi>Edward</hi> III. when all the Revenue of the Crown came into the Receipt, <hi>Pondere &amp; Numero.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It will diſcourage a great proportion of the Trade in <hi>England,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 292.</note> and ſo impair his Majeſty's Cuſtoms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Moneys of Gold and Silver formerly Coined, and abroad, being richer than thoſe intended, will be made, for the moſt part, hereby Bullion, and ſo Tranſported; which, I conceive, to be none of the leaſt Induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that hath drawn ſo many Goldſmiths to ſide in this Project, that they may be thereby Factors for the Strangers. And if in 5 <hi>Edward</hi> VI. 3 <hi>Mary,</hi> and 4 <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> it appeareth by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, that a Rumour only of an Alteration in Coin, cauſed ſuch Effects, puniſhing the Author of ſuch Reports with Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments, and Pillory, it cannot be doubted but the projecting a Change muſt be of far more Conſequence, and Danger to the State; and would be wiſhed, that the Actors, and Authors of ſuch Diſturbances in the Common Wealth, at all times hereafter, might undergo a Puniſhment proportionable.</p>
                  <p>It cannot be held (I preſume) an Advice of beſt Judgment, that layeth the loſs upon our ſelves, and the gain upon our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; for who is like to be in this time the greater Thriver? Is it not uſual, that the Stranger that tranſporteth over Moneys for Bullion, our own Goldſmiths that are their Brokers, and the Foreign <hi>Hedge-Minters</hi> of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> (which term becomes them well) have a freſh and full Trade by this Abatement.<note place="margin">293. ☜</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Experience hath taught us, that the enfeebling of Coin is but a ſhift for a while, as Drink to one in a Dropſie,<note place="margin">☜ 264.</note> to make him ſwell the more; but the State was never throughly cured, as we ſaw by <hi>Henry</hi> VIII's time, and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> until the Coin was made up again.</p>
                  <p>I cannot but then conclude, that if the proportion of Gold and Silver to each other, be brought into that Purity, by Advice of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37530:15"/>Artiſts, That neither may be too rich for the other; that the Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage may be reduced to ſome proportion of Neighbour-parts; and that the Iſſue of our Native Commodities may be brought to over-burthen the entrance of the Foreign,<note place="margin">☞</note> we need not ſeek any way of ſhift, but ſhall again ſee our Trade to flouriſh; the Mint (as the Pulſe of the Common Wealth) again to beat; and our Materials (by Induſtry) to be a Mine of Gold, and Silver to us, and the Honour, Juſtice, and Profit of his Majeſty (which we all wiſh, and work for) ſupported.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>III.</hi> The Committee's Anſwer, <hi>(2 September, 1626.)</hi> to the Minters Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for enhanſing the Money.</head>
                  <p>We conceive that the Officers of the Mint are bound by Oath, to diſcharge their ſeveral Duties in their ſeveral Places re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>But ſome ſuch things have been lately ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, that I fear</hi> we do <hi>not</hi> all wiſh, and work for the Honour, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and Profit of his Majeſty.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But we cannot conceive how they ſhould ſtand Ty'd by Oath, to account to his Majeſty the intrinſick value of all Foreign Coins, and how they agree with the Standard of this State; for all Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign States, do, for the moſt part, differ from us.</p>
                  <p>But to induce the neceſſity of the Propoſition, they produced two Inſtances, or Examples; the one from the <hi>Rix Dollar,</hi> and the other from the <hi>Royal</hi> of <hi>Eight,</hi> wherein they untruly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the Price and Value in our Moneys, and our Trade of both of them.</p>
                  <p>For whereas they ſay that the <hi>Rix Dollar</hi> weigheth Eighteen Peny weight,<note place="margin">Cottoni Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huma, <hi>p.</hi> 296, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> and Twelve Grains, and to be of the fineſt, at the Pound-weight, Ten Ounces Ten Peny weight, doth produce in Exchange 5 <hi>s.</hi> 2 <hi>d.</hi> Farthing of Sterling moneys. We do affirm that the ſame Dollar is Eighteen Peny weight, Eighteen Grains, and in Fineneſs, Ten Ounces 12 <hi>d.</hi> weight, equal to 4 <hi>s.</hi> 5 <hi>d. ob.</hi> of Sterling moneys, and is, at this time, in <hi>London</hi> at no higher Price, which is ſhort thereof by Thirteen Grains, and a half, fine Silver upon every Dollar, being 2 <hi>d.</hi> Sterling, or thereabouts, being the charge of Coinage, with a ſmall recompence to the Goldſmith, or Exchanger, to the Profit of <hi>England,</hi> 3 <hi>s.</hi> 6. <hi>d. per Cent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whereas they do in their circumſtance averr, that this Dollar runs in account of Trade amongſt the Merchants, at 5 <hi>s.</hi> 2 <hi>d. ob.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37530:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>Engliſh</hi> Money, it is moſt falſe: For the Merchants, and beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Men, proteſt the contrary; and that it paſſeth in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, according to the Intrinſick value only, 4 <hi>s.</hi> 5 <hi>d.</hi> ob. of the Sterling Money, or near thereabout, and no otherwiſe.</p>
                  <p>The Second inſtance is in the Royal of Eight, affirming that it weigheth 17 peny Weight, 12 Grains, and being but of the fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of 11 Ounces at the pound Weight, doth paſs in Exchange at 5 <hi>s.</hi> of our Sterling Moneys, whereby we loſe 6 <hi>s.</hi> 7 <hi>d.</hi> in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pound Weight. But having examined it by the beſt Artiſts, we find it to be 11 Ounces, 2 <hi>d.</hi> Weight Fine, and in Weight 17 peny Weight, 12 Grains, and a half, in every Royal of Eight,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pa.</hi> 297.</note> which is the charge of Coinage, and a ſmall overplus for the Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith's gain. And whereas they ſay that the ſaid Royal of Eight runs in account of Trade at 5 <hi>s.</hi> of his Majeſties, now, <hi>Engliſh</hi> Money; the Merchants do all affirm the contrary, and that it paſſeth only at 4 <hi>s.</hi> 4 <hi>ob.</hi> of the Sterling Monies, and no higher ordinarily.</p>
                  <p>And it muſt be ſtrange to believe that our Neighbours, the <hi>Netherlanders,</hi> would give for a pound Tale of our Sterling Silver, by what name ſoever it paſſeth, a greater quantity of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in the like Intrinſick value, by Exchange; or that our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants would knowingly, give a greater for a leſs to them, except by way of uſance. But the deceit is herein only, that they continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally varying their Coin, and crying it up at pleaſure, may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us for a time, in too high a reputation of pure Silver in it,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pa.</hi> 298.</note> upon Truſt, than there is unto a Tryal; and this, by no alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Coyn, unleſs we ſhould daily, as they, make his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Standard uncertain, can be prevented; which being the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Lands, Rents, and Commerce amongſt our ſelves at home, would render all uncertain, and ſo of neceſſity deſtroy the uſe of Money, and turn all to permutation of ſuch things, as were not ſubject to will or change.</p>
                  <p>And as they have miſtaken the ground of their Propoſition, ſo have they upon a ſpecious ſhow of ſome momentary and ſmall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to his Majeſty, reared up a vaſt, and conſtant, loſs unto him by this Deſign, if once effected. For as his Majeſty hath the largeſt proportion of any, both in the Entrances and Iſſues; ſo ſhould he, by ſo Enfeebling of his Coyn, become the greateſt loſer.</p>
                  <p>There needs no other Inſtance, than thoſe Degrees of diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the 18. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3 <hi>d.</hi> to this day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:37530:16"/>And for us then to raiſe our Coin at this time,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pa. 307.</hi>
                     </note> to Equal their Proportions, were but to render our ſelves to a perpetual uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty; for they will raiſe upon us daily, then again, which if we of courſe ſhould follow,<note place="margin">☞</note> elſe receive no profit by the preſent Change, we then deſtroy the Policy, Juſtice, Honour, and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of our State at home for ever.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>IV.</hi> In the Year aforeſaid <hi>1626,</hi> theſe Queſtions were propoſed to the Merchants, Mint-Maſters, and Goldſmiths, concerning the Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Silver Moneys.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Whether the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Moneys now currant, are not as dear as the Foreign of the Dollar, and Royall of 8, in the Intrinſick va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue in the uſual Exchanges, now made by the Merchants beyond Sea?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whether this advancing will not cauſe all the Silver Bulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that might be Tranſported in Maſs or Foreign Coin, to be Minted with the King's Stamp beyond Sea, and ſo Tranſported, and his Mint thereby ſet leſs on Work than now?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Whether the advancing the Silver Coin in <hi>England</hi> will not cauſe a Tranſportation of moſt of that, that is now Currant to be Minted in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and from them brought back again, whereby his Majeſties Mint will fail by the Exported benefit.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Whether the advancing the Silver Coin, if it produce the former Effects, will not cauſe the Markets to be unfurniſhed of preſent Coin, to drive the Exchange, when moſt of the Old will be uſed in Bullion?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Whether the higher we raiſe the Coin at home, we make not thereby our Commodities beyond Sea the cheaper?</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Whether the greateſt profit by this Enhaunſing, will not grow to the ill Members of the State, that have formerly culled the weightieſt Pieces, and ſold them to the Stranger-Merchants to be Tranſported.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>V.</hi> And at the ſame time, theſe general Rules were Collected out of the Conſultations at Court concerning Money, and Bullion.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Gold, and Silver, have a two-fold Eſtimation in the Intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, as they are Monies, they are the Princes Meaſures given to his People; and this is a Prerogative of Kings: In the Intrinſick,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37530:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>they are Commodities, valuing each other according to the plenty, or ſcarcity, and ſo all other Commodities by them; and that is the ſole Power of Trade.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Meaſures in a Kingdom ought to be conſtant: It is the Juſtice and Honour of the King; for if they be altered, all Men,<note place="margin">'Tis juſt now ſo with our Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> at that Inſtant, are deceived in their precedent Contracts, either for Lands or Money; and the King moſt of all; for no Man knoweth then, either what he hath, or what he oweth.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This made the Lord Treaſurer <hi>Burleigh,</hi> in 1573. when ſome Projectors had ſet on foot a matter of this nature, to tell them, that they were worthy to ſuffer death for attempting to put ſo great a diſhonour on the Queen, and detriment, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, upon the People; for to alter this publick Meaſure, is to leave all the Markets of the Kingdom unfurniſhed: And what will be the Miſchief, the Proclamations of 5 <hi>Ed.</hi> VI. 3 <hi>Mariae,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">5 Edw. VI. 3 Mariaet 4 Eliz.</note> and 4 <hi>Eliz.</hi> will manifeſt, when but a rumour of the like produced that Effect ſo far, that beſides the Faith of the Princes to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary delivered in their Edicts, they were enforced to cauſe the Magiſtrates in every Shire, reſpectively, to Conſtrain the People to furniſh the Markets, to prevent a Mutiny.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. To make this Meaſure then, at this time, ſhort, is to raiſe all Prizes, or to turn the Money, or Meaſure, into Diſiſe, or Bullion, when it is richer by ſeven in the hundred in the Maſs, than the new Monies, and yet of no more value in the Market.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Hence of neceſſity it muſt follow, that there will not in a long time be ſufficient Minted of the New, to drive the Exchange of the Kingdom; and ſo all Trade, at one Inſtant, at a ſtand, and, in the mean time, the Markets unfurniſh'd, which how it may concern the quiet of the State, is worthy care.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>And thus far as Money is a Meaſure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. Now as it is a Commodity, it is reſpected, and valued by the Intrinſick quality: And firſt the one Metal to the other.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. All Commodities are prized by plenty, or ſcarcity, by dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or cheapneſs, the one by the other: If therefore we deſire our Silver to buy Gold, as it of late hath done, we muſt let it be the Cheaper, and leſs in Proportion valued, and ſo contrary; for one equivalent Proportion in both will bring in neither. We ſee the proof thereof by the unuſual quantity of Gold, brought late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Mint by reaſon of the price; for we rate it above all other Countries, and Gold may be bought too dear. To furniſh then this way the Mint with both, is altogether impoſſible.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:37530:17"/>9. And, at this time, it was apparently proved both by the beſt Artiſts, and Merchants, moſt acquainted with the Exchange, in both the Examples of the Mint-Maſters in the <hi>Rix Dollar</hi> and <hi>Real of Eight,</hi> that Silver here is of equal value, and Gold above, with the Foreign parts in the Intrinſick, and that the fallacy, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Lords by the Mint-Maſters, is only in the Nominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Intrinſick quality.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. But if we deſire both, it is not raiſing of the value that doth it, but the balancing of Trade; for buy we in more then we ſell of other Commodities, be the Money never ſo high prized, we muſt part with it to make the diſproportion even: If we ſell more than we buy, the contrary will follow.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. And this is plain in <hi>Spain</hi>'s neceſſities; for ſhould that King advance to a double rate his <hi>Real</hi> of <hi>Eight,</hi> yet needing, by reaſon of the barrenneſs of his Country, more of Foreign Wares than he can counter vail, by Enchange with his own, he muſt part with his Money, and gaineth no more by Exhauncing his Coin, but that he payeth a higher price for the Commodities he buyeth, if his work of raiſing be his own. But if we ſhall make Improvement of Gold and Silver, being the Staple Commodity of his State, we then advancing the price of his, abaſe to him our own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. To ſhape this Kingdom to the faſhion of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> were to frame a Royal <hi>Monarch</hi> by a Society of Merchants. Their Country is a continual Fair, and ſo the price of Money muſt riſe and fall to fit their occaſions. We ſee this by raiſing the Exchange at <hi>Frankford</hi> and other Places at the uſual time of their Marts.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. The frequent and daily Change in the low Countries of their Monies, is no ſuch injuſtice to any there, as it would be here. For being all either Mechanicks or Merchants, they can Rate accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly their Labour or their Wares, whether it be Coin or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Merchandiſe, to the preſent condition of their Money in Exchange.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. And our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, to whoſe profeſſion it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belongs, do ſo, according to the juſt Intrinſick value of their Foreign Coin, in all Barter of Commodities, or Exchange, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept at uſance; which we, that are ruled and ty'd by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſick Meaſure of Money, in all our conſtant Reckonings and Annual Bargains at home, cannot do.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. And for us then to raiſe our Coin, at this time, to equal their Proportions, were but to render our ſelves to a perpetual incertainty, for they will raiſe upon us daily then again, which if
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37530:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>we of Courſe ſhould follow, elſe receive no Profit by this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Change, we then deſtroy the Policy, Juſtice, Honour, and Tranquility of our State at home for ever.</p>
                  <q>If we go on debaſing our Money, Manufacture, and Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>to make even with the</hi> Dutch, we may now in a very ſhort time undo the Nation; and there is nothing that can recover us at preſent, but the <hi>Balance, Regulation, and Advancement of Trade,</hi> which the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty hath ſo often recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his Parliament; and by which means <hi>Edward</hi> III. got that Advantage of invading <hi>France,</hi> and dealing with it as he did, to the great Honour, and Intereſt of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Edward</hi> III. having that Game to play with <hi>France,</hi> either he muſt win, or loſe it; his Spirit was too big to ſit ſtill; and yet,<note place="margin">Hiſtorical Diſcourſe of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the Government of <hi>England,</hi> from the firſt times to the Reign of <hi>Edward III.</hi> Printed, <hi>1647. Part 2. p. 64.</hi>
                     </note> pre-adviſing himſelf about the Poverty of the People, and that their Patience would be ſpent ſoon after their Supplies, if they continually ſaw much going out, and nothing coming in, he laid a Plat-form for the augmenting of the Treaſure of the Kingdom, as well for the benefit of the People, as of the Crown.</p>
                  <p>By Taxes.<note n="*" place="margin">P. 65. 1.</note> And altho' it be true that <hi>Edward</hi> III. was a King of many Taxes, above all his Predeceſſors; yet cannot this be imputed as a blot to his Honour, or Liberty of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. For the King was not ſo unwiſe, as either to deſire it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out evident cauſe, or to ſpend it in ſecret, or upon his own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Intereſt; nor ſo weak, and irreſolv'd, as not to employ himſelf, and his Soldiers, to the utmoſt, to bring to paſs his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions; nor ſo unhappy, as to fail of the deſirable Iſſue, of what he took in hand.</p>
                  <p>So as, tho' the People parted with much Money, yet the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom gained much Honour and Renown; and becoming a Terror to their Neighbours, enjoy'd what they had in fuller ſecurity, and ſo were no Loſers by the Bargain in the Concluſion.</p>
                  <p>For the People had, <hi>quid pro quo,</hi> by the Advance of Trade,<note place="margin">P. 66. 2. ☜</note> wherein the King ſhewed himſelf the <hi>Cape Merchant of the World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Certainly Men's Parts, in thoſe Times, were of vaſt reach, that could manage ſuch Wars, ſettle ſuch a Government, and lay ſuch a Foundation of a Treaſury by Trade, a thing neceſſary to this Iſland next unto its own being, as may appear, not only in regard of the Riches of this Nation, but in regard of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37530:18"/>Strength thereof, and in regard of the maintenance of the Crown: The two latter of which, being no other than a natural effluence of the former, it will be ſufficient to touch the ſame in order to the thing in hand.</p>
                  <p>Now as touching that,<note place="margin">☞</note> it is evident, that the Riches of any Nation are ſupported by the Conjuncture of three regards.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. That the natural Commodities of the Nation may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd.</item>
                     <item>II. That the poorer ſort of People be ſet on work.</item>
                     <item>III.<note place="margin">P. 67. 3.</note> That the Value of Money be rightly balanc'd.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. For as on the one part, tho' the People be never ſo laborious, if the natural Commodities of the Iſland be not improved by their Labour, the People can never grow much richer, than barely for Subſiſtence during their Labour.</p>
                  <q>And here let me humbly preſume to ſay,<note place="margin">☞</note> that ſo long as this Nation is over balanc'd by others in Trade, we can get nothing but by one anothers Loſs.</q>
                  <p n="2">2. The Endeavour were to advance Manufacture, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally ſuch of them, as are made of the ſtaple Commodities, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all which Wool had the Precedency, as being the moſt principal and ancient Commodity of the <hi>KINGDOM,</hi> and the Manufacture of Wool of long uſe, but had received little Encouragement before theſe Times.</p>
                  <p>For that it formerly had been the principal Flower in the <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Garden,<note place="margin">P. 68.</note> and nouriſhed from this Nation by the continual ſupply of Wool, that it received from hence.</p>
                  <p>Which was the principal Cauſe of the Ancient League, between the Houſe of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and this Crown.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Edward</hi> III. was too well acquainted with the <hi>Flemings</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,<note place="margin">P. Ditto.</note> by a joint Engagement with them in the Wars with <hi>France;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">☞</note> and therein had gained ſo good an Opinion amongſt them, that he might have adventured to have chang'd a Complement for a Courteſie.</p>
                  <p>The Staples, beyond the Sea, were now taken away: He now inhibiteth the Importation of Foreign Cloths; and having gained theſe two ſteps onward of his way, he repreſents to the <hi>Flemings</hi> their unſettled Condition,<note place="margin">11. Edw. 3. Cap. 2, 3, 5.</note> by theſe bordering: Wars with <hi>France,</hi> the peaceable Condition of <hi>England,</hi> and Freedom of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:37530:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Then propounds to them an Invitation to come over into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. Ditto. ☜</note> promiſeth them ſhare, and ſhare-like with his own People, with ſuch other Immunities, as they took his offer, came over, and brought their Manufacture with them, which could never after be recall'd.</p>
                  <p>So as now the Wool, and the Manufacture live together;<note place="margin">P. Ditto.</note> and like to Man and Wife, ſo long as they care for one another, both will thrive; but if they come to play their Games apart, both will be Loſers in the Concluſion.</p>
                  <p>Another means to advance Trade, was the ſettling of a Rule upon Exportation, and Importation,<note place="margin">P. 70. 3. ☜</note> which wrought a double Effect.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. That Importation brought in more Profit, than Exportation disburſed.</item>
                     <item>II. That both Exportation, and Importation, were made by Shipping belonging to this Nation, ſo far as it did conſiſt with the benefit of this Nation.</item>
                     <item>III. That the Exportation was regulated to the Over-plus, ſaving the main Stock at home.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. The truth of the firſt will be evident from this ground,<note place="margin">P. Ditto. ☜</note> That no Nation can be rich, that receives more dead Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from abroad, than it can ſpend at home, or vend into foreign Parts; eſpecially if it be vended in its proper kind, and not in Money.</p>
                  <p>And therefore the Laws provided,<note place="margin">27 Edw. III. ☜</note> That no Merchant ſhould export more Money than he imported; and what he imported, muſt have been of the New Stamp, which it ſeems was inferiour in value to the Old.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Second is no leſs beneficial; for as it is in War,<note place="margin">P. 71.</note> ſo in all Trades, the greater the number is, that is employ'd, the more effectual the iſſue will be.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Third, and Laſt Conſideration, is as neceſſary as any of the former; for if Trade be maintained out of the main Stock,<note place="margin">☜</note> the Kingdom in time muſt be brought to Penury.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> laſt means that was ſet on foot, in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> III. for the Advance of Trade, was the regulating the Mint,<note place="margin">P. 74. ☜</note> and the Currant of Money.</p>
                  <p>This is the Life and Soul of Trade; for tho' Exchange of Commodities may do much, yet it cannot be for all, becauſe it
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37530:19"/>is not the Lot of all to have Exchangeable Commodities, nor to work for Apparel and Victual.</p>
                  <p>Now in the managing of this Trick of Money,<note place="margin">☞</note> Two things are principally looked unto.<note place="margin">P. Ditto.</note>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. That the Money be good and currant.</item>
                     <item>2. That it ſhould be plentiful.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>As touching the Excellency of the Money, ſeveral Rules were made,<note place="margin">25 Edw. 3. Stat. 5. cap 13. 6 Edw. 3. cap. 2, and 3.</note> as againſt embaſing of Money, againſt Foreign Money not made Currant, and againſt Counterfeit and Falſe Money.</p>
                  <p>For according to the Goodneſs of the Money,<note place="margin">☞</note> ſo will the Trade be more or leſs.</p>
                  <p>For the Merchant will rather loſe in the Price of his Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity in Money,<note place="margin">☞</note> than in Exchange for other Commodities, becauſe the value thereof is leſs certain, and the Tranſportation more chargeable.</p>
                  <p>As touching the Plenty of Money, that is as neceſſary to the Advance of the Trade,<note place="margin">P. Ditto.</note> as of the goodneſs of it.</p>
                  <p>For according to the Plenty thereof,<note place="margin">☞</note> will be the Plenty of the Manufactures, becauſe Handy-crafts having no Commodities, but their labour, cannot work for Exchange, nor can Exchange ſupply rents and maintenance to the greater ſort of People.</p>
                  <p>To this end therefore it is provided againſt melting of Money, and Exportation of Silver and Gold.<note place="margin">6 Edw. 3. cap. 2.3. 17 Rich. 2 c 1.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>And yet to encourage, or not diſcourage importation of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and Gold,<note place="margin">☞</note> liberty was given to every man to export ſo much as they did import, provided that what they carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way muſt be of the New Stamp,<note place="margin">This is anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and I take it to be true Policy: And ſee <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Trade,</hi> p. <hi>34.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> That the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of our Moneys in Trade of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandice, is a means to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our Treaſures.</note> or minted in this Nation.</p>
                  <p>By this means, Bullion came in with probability that much thereof would remain in the Nation, in lien of Commodities ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported; or if not the greater part, yet at leaſt the Mint gained, and that was ſome benefit to the Nation.</p>
                  <p>And tho' the Mint was ſettled by the Parliament, yet the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change was left to the Directory of the King and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil; becauſe the Exchange is an uncertain thing, ſubject to ſudden alterations in other Nations, and its neceſſary that in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, it be as ſuddenly balanced with the Exchange in other Countries, or in a ſhort time the Nation may receive extream Damage.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:37530:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>And laſtly to watch the courſe of the Exchange in Foreign Parts, and to parallel the courſe thereof in this Land thereunto;<note place="margin">☜</note> for otherwiſe the Publick muſt neceſſarily ſuffer ſo long as pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Men ſeek their own particular Intereſt only in their courſe of Trade.</p>
                  <p>That there be more of Publick Good in Merchandice,<note place="margin">☜</note> and the Confuſion of Trade taken away. It were well the Myſteries of Exchange were more publickly known; and alſo that there were a Committee of Trade, mixed with the chief able Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, to continue always, who ſhould ſtill be on the diſcovery and ſtudy for the Improvement of Trade. <hi>Engliſh Intereſt,</hi> P. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>For there are open as well as private Enemies to the publick Good, as I find particularly by a Printed Paper.</p>
                  <p>Intituled,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For encouraging the Coyning Silver Money in</hi> England, <hi>and after for keeping is here.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which is a parcel of Pretenſion, and <hi>all ſtuff</hi> as the <hi>ſhort Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations thereon</hi> plainly ſheweth. Pag. 2. 3. and pag. 4. 5. it affirms, that the Reaſon why we have not had more Money come to our Mint, is in ſhort this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>England</hi> ſending more conſumable Commodities to <hi>Spain,</hi> than it receives from thence; the Merchants, who managed that Trade bring back the Over-plus in Bullion, which at their return they ſell as a Commodity. The Chapmen that give higheſt for this are, as in all caſes (of buying and ſelling) thoſe who can make moſt Profit by it; and thoſe are the Returners of our Money by Exchange, into thoſe Countries where our Debts any way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted make a need of it: For they getting 6.8.10. <hi>&amp;c. per Cent.</hi> according to the want and demand of Money from <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> there, and according to the risk of the Sea, buy up this Bullion, aſſoon as it comes in to ſend it to their Correſpondents in thoſe Parts, to make good their Credit for the Bills they have drawn on them, and ſo can give more for it than the Mint rate, <hi>i e.</hi> more than an equal weight of Mill'd Money, for an equal weight of Standard Bullion, they being able to make more Profit of it by Returns.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:37530:20"/>Suppoſe the Balance of our Trade with <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> were in all other Commodities equal; but that in the laſt <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Sale we bought of them of <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Commodities, to the value of a Million, to be paid in a Month, a Million muſt be return'd into <hi>Holland;</hi> this preſently raiſes the Exchange, and the Traders in Exchange ſell their Bills at high rates; but the Ballance of Trade being (as is ſuppos'd, in the Caſe) equal in all other Commodities, this Million can no way be repay'd to their Correſpondents on whom thoſe Bills were drawn, but by ſending them Money or Bulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to reimburſe them.</p>
                  <p>This is the true Reaſon why the Bullion brought from <hi>Spain</hi> is not carried to the Mint to be Coyn'd, but bought by Traders in Foreign Exchange,<note place="margin">☞</note> and Exported by them to ſuppply the overplus of our Expences there, which are not paid for by our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>In <hi>the true Engliſh Intereſt</hi> publiſhed 1674,<note place="margin">1674.</note> and fore-quoted, I find <hi>pa.</hi> 3. and <hi>Ca.</hi> 2. the following particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>That Nation that values Money moſt, ſhall have moſt of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Which (as he muſt mean them) are confuted by his own words immediately following.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Wherefore it is good that the value of Coyn be always ſomewhat higher, than in our Neighbour Nations, ſo can we not fail of having it from them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">☞</note> If we, and all Nations, ſhould think ſo, the World would (to out do one another) raiſe their Coin to the <hi>higheſt</hi> value, untill (to the undoing of themſelves) they brought it to nothing worth, and ſo to be of no uſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Alſo to keep Money in a Nation, it is good to allay it a little, and to Coin much ſmall Money.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Providence hath ſo ordered it for the general good of Mankind, that one Nations, like one Mans meat, may be another Nations Poyſon; and that which is good Policy in <hi>Holland,</hi> may in <hi>England</hi> be great Imprudence.</p>
                  <p>If then his Majeſty ſhall be pleaſed,<note place="margin">Cottoni Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huma, <hi>p.</hi> 198. 199.</note> by advice of his Council, to advantage himſelf any otherwiſe by Coynage, it will be ſafer to do it upon a ſimple Metal, than by any Implyant, or better ſute, which well govern'd States, both Modern, and Ancient uſed: For <hi>Rome</hi> in her Increaſe and greateſt pitch of Glory,<note place="margin">☞</note> had their Money <hi>aere, argento, oaur puto puro;</hi> and ſo have all the Monarchies
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37530:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>abſolute at this day in Chriſtendom.<note place="margin">Ditto <hi>p.</hi> 199.</note> And I believe it may be wrought to his Majeſty of good value, and to the State of much caſe, if it may be put in practice with diſcreet caution, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Reſolution; for the danger only may be in the venting the quantity, which may clog the State, with uſeleſs Money, or extenſion of the Example, which may work in, by degrees, an Embaſement of Bullion.</p>
                  <p>And the Form, and Figure may with an Engine ſo ſubtilly be Milled, that the charge will prevent all practice of falſe play.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pa.</hi> 200.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Beſides, it cannot but prevent much waſt of Silver,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pa.</hi> 201.</note> that is by the minting Pence, and half Pence occaſion'd, there will be no cauſe hereafter to cut any Bullion into proportion ſo apt for loſs.</p>
                  <p>And as to our Silver and Gold Money. <hi>Juſt ſo much miſchief,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Fleet-woods</hi> Ser. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Clipping. Pa. <hi>7. 8. 9.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>and injury muſt needs be done to every individual Man that takes it, as there is wanting of the uſual Weight, and fineneſs in each ſingle Piece, and ſo much is stollen from every Man, as there is leſs given him, than he ſhould receive: And this adminiſters occaſion to people, either Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, or Natives, to cheat us even with true Silver; for they may Coyn a great deal of true Silver; and,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">☞</note> 
                     <hi>putting it off under the ſhelter of clip'd Money, may gain thereby at leaſt one third. And what one gains ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loſeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſuppoſe ſuch a Famine ſhould befall us, as befell the Jews, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42. when <hi>Jacob</hi> ſent his ten Sons, <hi>to buy Corn in</hi> Egypt, with <hi>Moneyfull weight, and currant with the Merchant;</hi> And in this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine we ſhould be forced to go to <hi>Holland</hi> to buy food, from whence ſo much of our <hi>hedgminted</hi> Money comes, if we ſhould car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the ſame back again to them, we ſhould have but their <hi>peny worth</hi> for our <hi>peny weight,</hi> which would be a very ſlender pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion; and if we ſhould adventure to put our <hi>droſs Money</hi> upon them, as we do upon one another, we might chance to be ſerv'd (in alluſion to our Money) as the <hi>Meſſengers</hi> were by <hi>Hunun</hi> when <hi>he ſhaved off the one half of their Beards, and cut off their Garments in the middle, even to their Buttocks, and ſent them away.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Alſo to bring in the old Gold again, it were well the broad Pieces might go for</hi> 24 <hi>Shillings, and the</hi> 22 <hi>Shillings for</hi> 26 <hi>Shillings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whatever Gold is gone out of the Nation, hath been drawn from us, either by the neceſſity of War, or by the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balance of Trade, and if we ſhould receive our old Gold again as 24, and 26 Shillings, we ſhould loſe as much by each Piece, as each Piece was overvalued. For the Importers of them would have Goods in return, or Bills of Exchange, wherein the reſt of the World have the advantage of us, as well as in Trade; and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37530:21"/>what this Nation doth loſt by Exchange,<note place="margin">☞</note> might be ſhrewdly gueſs'd at, if our Law was like that excellent Law of <hi>Franch,</hi> which doth oblige all Bankrupts to produce their Books; and if it was ſo in <hi>England</hi> it would be much for the publick Intereſt, and for the credit of many unfortunate Perſons in particular.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>It is no ſmall ſign of a Bank-rupting Nation,<note place="margin">☞</note> when Silver, or Gold, in a Kingdom, go for more than they are worth: And it is the Policy of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and others, added to the neceſſity of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, that make our Guineas go at 25 Shillings, which is a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Grievance, next to that of our light, and droſs Money; for the Nation, conſidering the Nature of our Exchange, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it loſeth at leaſt 5 <hi>s.</hi> a piece.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Naples</hi> (a place that was as notorious, as the People that liv'd in it) the Coin of the Kingdom was Clipt as ours is, and it had fallen into as deep a Conſumption, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had it not been for the Marquiſs <hi>de Carpi,</hi> of whom Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> (Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>) gives the following Account.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>And how, <hi>(ſaid he,)</hi> can a Man expect to find his Religion here, where the common Maxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s of Juſtice, and Mercy, were not ſo much as known.<note place="margin">Letters <hi>pa.</hi> 166.</note> An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> can never forget the lively reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that a Roman Prince made to me, upon the folly of all thoſe ſevere oppreſſions,<note place="margin">☞</note> which as they drive away the Inhabitants, ſo they reduce thoſe are left to a great degeneracy of ſpirit by their neceſſities.</p>
                     <p>Indeed if <hi>Spain</hi> had been ſo happy as to have ſuch <hi>Vice-Roys,</hi> and Governours,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pa.</hi> 167.</note> as it hath now in <hi>Naples,</hi> their Affairs could not have declined ſo faſt as they have done. The Marquiſs of <hi>Carpi,</hi> in his youth, intended to have taken ſo ſevere a revenge of an injury, that he thought the late King of <hi>Spain</hi> did him in an Amour, that he deſigned the blowing him up by Gunpowder when he was in the Council Chamber; but that Crime was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered in time, and was not only forgiven him, in conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the greatneſs of his Family, he being the Son of <hi>Don Lewis de Haro;</hi> but after that he was made, for ſeveral years, Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour at <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He now is <hi>Vice-Roy</hi> of <hi>Naples,</hi> and is the only Governour of all the Places through which I paſſed, that is without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on beloved, and eſteemed by all ſorts of People: For, during the few years of his Miniſtry, he hath redreſſed ſuch Abuſes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37530:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>that ſeemed paſt cure, and that required an Age to correct them.</p>
                     <p>He hath redreſſed the Inſolence of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſo much at <hi>Naples,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">P. 168.</note> that the Natives have no occaſion to complain of the haughtineſs of their Maſters; for he proceeds againſt the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> with no leſs ſeverity when they give cauſe for it, than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Neapolitans.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He hath taken the pay of the Soldiers ſo immediately into his own care, that they who before his coming were half naked,<note place="margin">☜</note> and robbed ſuch as paſſed on the Streets of <hi>Naples</hi> in day light, are now exactly paid, well Diſciplin'd, and ſo decently Cloathed, that it is a pleaſure to ſee them: He examines their Muſters alſo ſo exactly, that he is ſure not to be cheated by falſe Liſts.</p>
                     <p>He hath brought the Markets and Weights of <hi>Naples</hi> to a true exactneſs; and whereas the Bread was generally too light,<note place="margin">☜</note> he has ſent for Loaves out of the ſeveral places of the Markets, and weighed them himſelf; and by ſome ſevere puniſhments on thoſe that ſold the Bread too light, he hath brought this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to a juſt regulation.</p>
                     <p>He hath alſo brought the Courts of Judicature,<note place="margin">☜</note> that were thought generally very corrupt, to reputation again, and it is believed he hath Spyes to watch, in caſe the Trade of Brioes is found to be ſtill going on.</p>
                     <p>He hath fortified the Palace which was before his time ſo much expoſed,<note place="margin">☜</note> that it would have been no hard thing to have made deſcent upon it.</p>
                     <p>But the two things that raiſes his Reputation moſt,<note place="margin">P. 169.</note> are his extirpating the <hi>Banditti,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">☜</note> and the Regulation of the Coin which he hath taken in hand.</p>
                     <p>It is well enough known, what a plague the <hi>Banditti,</hi> have been to the Kingdom, for they going in Troops, not only robbed the Country, but were able to reſiſt an ordinary body of Soldiers if they had ſet on them.</p>
                     <p>Theſe travelled about ſeeking for ſpoil all the Summer long;<note place="margin">☜</note> but in Winter, they were harboured by ſome of the <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Barons who gave them quarters, and thereby did not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect their own Lands, but had them, as ſo many Inſtruments to execute their Revenge on their Enemies.</p>
                     <p>This was well known at <hi>Naples,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">☜</note> and there was a Council that had a care of reducing the <hi>Banditti</hi> committed to them, who as they catched ſome few, and hanged them, ſo they fined ſuch Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons as gave them harbour, and it was believed that thoſe Fines amounted to near 150 Crowns a year.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:37530:22"/>And thus the Diſeaſe went on; only now and then there was a little Blood let out,<note place="margin">☞</note> which never went to the bottom of the Diſtemper.</p>
                     <p>But when the preſent Vice-Roy entred upon the Government, he was reſolved to extirpate all the Banditti; and he firſt let all the Barons underſtand, that if they harboured them any more, a little Fine would not ſave them;<note place="margin">☞</note> but that he would proceed againſt him with the utmoſt Severity, and by this means the Banditti could find no Winter-Quarters; ſo they betook them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſome Faſtneſſes among the Hills, and reſolv'd to make good the Paſſes, and to accommodate themſelves the beſt they could amidſt the Mountains.</p>
                     <p>The Vice Roy ſent a great Body againſt them;<note place="margin">☞</note> but they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended themſelves for ſome time vigorouſly, and in one Sally they killed 500 Men; but at laſt ſeeing they were like to be hard preſs'd, and that the Vice-Roy intended to come againſt them in Perſon, they excepted of the Terms that he offer'd them, which was a Pardon for what was paſt, both as to Life and Galleys, and 6 <hi>d.</hi> a day for their Entertainment in Priſon, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Life, or the Vice-Roy's pleaſure, and ſo they ſurrendred themſelves.</p>
                     <p>They are kept in a large Priſon, and now and then (as he ſees cauſe for it,) he ſends ſome few up and down to ſerve in Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
                     <p>And thus beyond all Men's Expectation, he finiſhed this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in a very few Months; and the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> that hath been ſo long a Scene of Pillage and Robbery, is now ſo much changed, that in no place of <hi>Europe</hi> do Subjects enjoy a more entire Security.</p>
                     <p>As for the Coin,<note place="margin">P. 170.</note> it is as all the other <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Money is ſo ſubject to Clipping,<note place="margin">☞</note> that the whole Money of <hi>Naples</hi> is now light, and far below the true value; ſo the Vice-Roy has reſolved to redreſs this.</p>
                     <p>He conſiders that the crying down of Money, that paſſeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Publick Credit,<note place="margin">☞</note> is a robbing of thoſe in whoſe hands the Money happens to be, when ſuch Proclamations are put out; and therefore he takes a Method that is more general, in which every one will bear his ſhare, ſo that none will be cruſh'd by it.</p>
                     <p>He hath laid ſome Taxes on the whole Kingdom, and hath got a great many to bring in ſome Plate to be coined;<note place="margin">☞</note> and when he hath thus prepared ſuch a quantity as may ſerve for the Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37530:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>that is neceſſary; he intends to call in all the Old Money, and to give out new Money for it.</p>
                     <p>Thus doeth this Vice-Roy ſet ſuch a Pattern to the other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> that if many would follow it,<note place="margin">☜</note> the State of their Affairs would be ſoon altered.</p>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>One of our Hiſtorians (<hi>W. Hemingford Anno</hi> 1180.) tells us,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fleetwood</hi>'s Sermon ab ut Clipping. <hi>p. 17.</hi>
                     </note> that in <hi>Henry</hi> II. time, the Money of the Kingdom was ſo corrupt, that it was fain to be chang'd and called in; it was indeed neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, but it fell exceeding hard upon the Poor and Country Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: So it was alſo in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> III. upon calling in the Old and Clipp'd Money (<hi>M. Paris Anno</hi> 1240.) by a Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the People were more diſtreſs'd, than if Corn had been at half a Crown a Buſhel; (which was then, I believe, equal to Twelve or Fourteen Shillings now) for the new Money was not yet come to their great Towns, and when it was, they receiv'd no more new than their old came to by weight; paying alſo over and above, Thirteen Pence in the Pound for Coinage; ſo that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the loſs of time, and the great Charge they were at, to come to the ſeveral Places of Exchange, they were ſent away with hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Twenty Shillings for every Thirty, that they brought along with them, <hi>Arctabatur Populus, non mediocriter damnificatus.</hi> The People were ſtraitned, and receiv'd no ſmall damage; they loſt, you ſee, one third. The Poor ſtill ſuffered moſt, and ſo it will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be, for a ſmall Weight is heavy to the weak and faint; and a little loſs grievous to ſuch as have but little.</p>
                  <p>The Conſideration of this, and the preceding paſſages of the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and the Circumſtances we are under; made me apply my ſelf to ſome Perſons, who I thought would give me ſome account how the Coin at <hi>Naples</hi> was regulated; and Mr. <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrey Levermore</hi> did me the favour to procure me the following Letter, from Mr. <hi>William Sealy,</hi> who lived a Merchant many years at <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>SIR,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Old Money at <hi>Naples</hi> being extremely dipt and falſified, cauſed the exchange from all parts of <hi>Naples</hi> in Ieſs than two years time, to riſe about 25. <hi>per Cent.</hi> which likewiſe made a great alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in Trade, and all Foreign Commodities to riſe proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="44" facs="tcp:37530:23"/>To remedy which, there was no way but by making new Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, which they were about 7 Years conſulting and bringing to paſs, at laſt it was reſolved, that the new Money ſhould be made about 10 <hi>per Cent.</hi> of worſe allay than the old was; and about 10 <hi>per Cent.</hi> leſs in weight than the good old Money really was, and this to prevent the Carrying it out of the Kingdom.</p>
                        <p>And in order to this, the Viceroy contracted with moſt of the Principal Merchants in <hi>Naples,</hi> for to furniſh him with ſo many Tunns of Silver within a limited time; and to be re-inburſed with a conſiderable allowance from the Cuſtoms and other Gaballs in that Kingdom.</p>
                        <p>So that when a great quantity of Mony was made, Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were ſent throughout the Kingdom; that within the ſpace of Three Months, all the old Money ſhould be brought in, and they ſhould receive a new Duckat for an old one, though never ſo much clipp'd, provided the Coin was good: But if falſe, they returned it them, cut a ſunder, to make the moſt of it they could.</p>
                        <p>To effect which great quantities of Monies were ſent into every Province and Banks erected; and People appointed in every Town and City, to receive the old Man and deliver out the new, and if any remained after the above-limited time, it was to be brought into the Mint, and the Owners to receive only the weight of new Money for the weight of old.</p>
                        <p>All this was very punctually obſerved and performed; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the City of <hi>Naples</hi> there are Eleven Banks, which keep almoſt all the Caſh of the Kingdom, and all publick payments, either Bills of Exchange or otherwiſe cannot lawfully be paid, but by a Note of one of the ſaid Banks, which are all regiſtred.</p>
                        <p>Therefore all the Money we receive, we generally pay into the ſaid Banks, and they receive it, not only by tale, but by weight; and ſo they pay it out again, when we come for any; but if any be found of a falſe Coin or Braſs, they cut it a ſunder before your face, and then give it you again to make the moſt of it.</p>
                        <p>This New Money being about 20 <hi>per Cent,</hi> worſe than the good Old Money, cauſeth the exchange to continue ſtill high, and all Foreign Commodities to bear a Price accordingly, which can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be remedied, but by laying ſuch a Tax on the People, as will equalize it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which muſt not be done in ſuch a Kingdom, where the Peoples Inclinations are addicted to Rebellion.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:37530:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>By that of <hi>the Exchange, the Old Ducats never ſo much clipp'd, and the New ones Ten per Cent. allay'd and lighten'd to prevent their Exportation,</hi> (which looks like <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Policy) it may be ſeen and conſidered what it is in conſequence to have ſuch little, light, and baſe Money in a Kingdom, that is over-balanc'd by diſadvanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Trade, as ours hath long been, and under ſome other ſuch Circumſtances as we are.</p>
                  <p>We ſhould have been more <hi>happy,</hi> if <hi>other Men's harms</hi> had made us more <hi>aware</hi> of our own: And when our New Coin comes to be minted (as it muſt be, <hi>tantum in Pecunia, quantum in Maſſa,</hi> or elſe this Nation muſt ſuffer like the <hi>Neapolitan</hi>) we are to take care <hi>to receive it, not only by Tale, but by Weight, and to cut aſunder all falſe Coin,</hi> that the <hi>Hedg-minters</hi> may not make more private Merchandice thereof; and that their Publick Factors may not have a continued Impudence of Crying, <hi>Have you any Braſs Money, or broken Silver?</hi> in the open Streets.</p>
                  <p>What <hi>another-gates Cry</hi> we ſhall have, when our <hi>Droſs money</hi> comes to be cry'd down, and our <hi>Clipp'd Money</hi> to be call'd in, I cannot imagine; but if I may judge a little by the laſt calling in of our Tinn Farthings, and the crying down the Lead ones, I may fear much (as Mr. <hi>Fleetwood</hi> ſaith) <hi>the Cry will be, like that of</hi> Egypt,<note place="margin">P. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>loud, and univerſal;</hi> (unleſs our Coin and Commerce be conſider'd together) <hi>for every Family will be a looſer; but it will fall ſevereſt upon the Poor; who from a little can ſpare none.</hi> And therefore they ſhould be the more ſpared, if the People in general ſhould come to be taxed towards the re-minting of our Money.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>But I think, it is great pity, that poor innocent People ſhould pay for that guilt, and villainy; whereby many rich Men muſt have advanced very much Wealth, or <hi>no ſmall Gain.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>For it doth not ſeem very probable, that ſo much Money ſhould be ſpent by thoſe poor and mean Wretches, who are commonly diſcovered to live by this unjuſt and wicked practice. The Summ is much too big for-them, and one cannot well account, how almoſt all the Old Silver, that circles round the Nation, ſhould come into thoſe Clippers hands in the compaſs of a few Years.</hi> It muſt come from <hi>ſuch as go up and down, whether in City, or Country, to procure broad Money,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 27.</note> 
                     <hi>and from ſuch as ſell theſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37530:24"/>People broad Money for great gain.</hi> And ſince ſuch great gain muſt needs have been made by thoſe <hi>Mongers and Monopolizers of Money,</hi> it would be well if ſome <hi>Ways and Means</hi> could be found out to raiſe ſome <hi>Fund</hi> on them, for the recoining the clipp'd and corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted Caſh of the Kingdom, which (together with the regulating of Commerce) muſt be done, with more than <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſpeed, and better policy; or elſe <hi>the whole ſtock thereof will not be worth a Chip.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>And as theſe <hi>Mongers, and Monopolizers of Money;</hi> ſo thoſe of Merchandize ſhould be likewiſe taxed towards the re-coining the Caſh of the Kingdom; I mean in an extraordinary manner.</p>
                  <p>For,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reflections on the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>and Royal</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frican <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> &amp;c. P. 1.</note> as Mr. <hi>Roger Coke</hi> ſaith, Monopolies are the moſt wicked, tyrannical, and injurious Uſurpations over other Men, and the greateſt violations of the Law of Nature of any other; and are ſo much worſe than Robbery, by how much the quality of them is worſe, and the extent farther.</p>
                  <p>Nor are theſe Monopolies leſs impolitick,<note place="margin">P. 2.</note> than they are injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; for the greateſt benefit which any Country or Kingdom en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys, is by the imployment of the Inhabitants, which being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd to a few, the reſidue become a Burden to that Country to maintain them, and thoſe alſo become dangerous to that Country for want of Imployment. From whence it follows, that they muſt either ſeek unlawfull means to ſubſiſt, or flee into other Countries to get ſubſiſtance there, which is as much a benefit to thoſe Countries, as it is a loſs to this.</p>
                  <p>The Prerogative of the <hi>Eaſt-India,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 9.</note> and Royal <hi>African</hi> Company extend to two thirds of the Circumference of the Globe of the Earth.</p>
                  <p>And,<note place="margin">P. 10.16</note> not to take Notice how far the export of our Woollen Manufactures have been reſtrain'd in other Countries of <hi>England,</hi> the County of <hi>Suffolk</hi> (before the <hi>African</hi> Company was incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated) vended yearly 25000 Clothes to <hi>Africa;</hi> but, about two Years after, the Clothiers in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> as they did before, endeavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to have vented their Clothes in the <hi>African</hi> Trade, but they were not permitted, and the Company would take off but 500, and thoſe at ſcarce half the Prizes they were ſold at before.</p>
                  <p>The Companies returns into <hi>England</hi> from <hi>Africk</hi> are princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally <hi>Gold Duſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 11.</note> which is ſo much leſs, as the reſtraint by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany is more.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:37530:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>And they rais'd the Price of Elephants Teeth ſo high, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> could bring them in cheaper, and ſo work the Manufactures of them cheaper than the poor <hi>Engliſh</hi> could work them, and this being a Manufacture of <hi>Holland,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> by <hi>the Act of Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> may import them to the great prejudice of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers. And whither this be not a grievance, is ſubmitted to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>But ſee what another <hi>Coke</hi> ſaith <hi>of Monopoliſts, Propounders and Projectors</hi> in the third part of his <hi>Inſtitutes</hi> pa. 181. <hi>Ca.</hi> 85.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A Monopoly (ſaith he) is an Inſtitution, or allowance by the King, by his Grant, Commiſſion, or otherwiſe, to any Perſon, or Perſons, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Politick, or Corporate, of, or for the ſole buying, ſelling, making, working or uſing of any thing, whereby others are reſtrain'd from the Freedom they had before, and hindered in their lawfull Trade.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For the Word Monopoly, <hi>dicitur</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, i. ſolo, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, i. <hi>vendere.</hi> — But the Law of the Realm in this point is grounded upon the Law of God, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the nether or upper Milſtone to pledge, for thou takest a Man's Life to pledge.</hi> Whereby it appeareth, that a Man's Trade is accounted his Life, becauſe it maintaineth his Life: And therefore the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopoliſt, that taketh away a Man's Trade, taketh away his Life, and is ſo much the more odious, becauſe he is <hi>Vir ſanguinis:</hi> Againſt theſe Inventers, and Propounders of evil things, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt hath ſpoken, Rom. 1.30. <hi>Inventores Malorum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>digni ſunt Morte.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:37530:25"/>
               <head>PART IV.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>I Am no Enemy to our Merchants, having adventured my Life for their Fortunes, and ſhould be as ready to do ſo again; for (as the Earl of <hi>Northampton</hi> ſaith in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Grievances) <hi>they are a People not only to be reſpected, but to be pray'd for; they are</hi> Vena Porta (ſaith my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> in his Eſſays) <hi>and if they flouriſh not, a Kingdom may have ſtrong Limbs, but it will have empty Veins, and nouriſh little;</hi> and Mr. <hi>Mun</hi> (in his <hi>Engliſh Treaſure by Foreign Trade</hi>) calls them <hi>the Stewards of the Kingdoms ſtock by way of Commerce with other Nations. A work</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of no leſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, than truſt, and ought to be performed with great Skill and Conſcience; that ſo the private gain may ever accompany the publick good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the publick good of the Nation can never proſper under <hi>the unjuſt Stewardſhip,</hi> and ill managery of Monopoliſts.</p>
                  <p>So long as we are more reſtrain'd than other Nations, and as it were ſtrangled in Trade, the face of <hi>Albion's State-Affairs</hi> cannot but look black, and loſe its complection of <hi>Nature's white Boy,</hi> and <hi>Britannia</hi> will be call'd <hi>Languent,</hi> (according to the Title of that excellent Book,) until <hi>the GREAT</hi> is dwindl'd into <hi>Little BBRITAIN.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But now we have a King, that is conſtantly recommending the Trade of the Nation (which is the Nerve and Sinew of War,) if we would add Art to Nature, give Trade its due <hi>liberty and property,</hi> fullneſs of People, Manufacture, and Exportation, (as the <hi>French,</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> do to theirs,) we ſhould quickly exceed them both in Trade, as we have naturally a greater advantage for the over-ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:37530:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>England is,</hi> (by Nature, and Scituation) <hi>the Center of Trade; but</hi> (for want of Art, and Encouragement thereunto) <hi>it ſerves,</hi> as the Center doth, <hi>to make the Circumference.</hi> And had it not been <hi>Puteus inexhanſtus, ubi Multa abundant,</hi> as Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> IV. us'd to ſay of it, it might have been drein'd as dry of ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Treaſure, as it is of advantageous Trading.</p>
                  <p>But our People are of a middle Temper (and do ſtill continue ſo) according to their Climate, and not (as it ſhould now be) according to the Temper of their Prince; for when the Majeſty of a King is moſt excellent, Mediocrity in the Subjects is too mean.</p>
                  <p>The Northern Melancholy, and the Southern Choler,<note place="margin">Hiſt. Diſcr. <hi>p.</hi> 300.</note> meeting in their general Conſtitution, do render them ingenious and active; which nouriſh'd alſo under the Wings of Liberty, inſpires a Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage generous, and not ſoon out of breath. Active they are, and ſo nigh to pure Act, that nothing hurts them more than much quiet, of which they had little Experience, from their firſt Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migration, till the time of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt; who, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering all Enmity, ſpake Peace abroad to his Enemies, and ſang Lullaby at home to his Friends.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>It is apparent (ſaith Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> to the ſaid King <hi>James</hi>) that no three Kingdoms in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> can compare with your Majeſty's for ſupport of Traffick,<note place="margin">Remains, <hi>p.</hi> 185.</note> and continual Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for your People within themſelves, having ſo many means both by Sea, and Land, to enrich your Majeſty's Coffers,<note place="margin">Which he rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons up, and ſhows the King how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſand Men they might employ, and how many Millions of Money they would get from the World.</note> mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply your Navy, enlarge your Traffick, make your Kingdom powerful, and your People rich.</p>
                  <p>Yet through Idleneſs they are poor; wanting Employment, many of your Land, and Coaſt-Towns much ruinated,<note place="margin">We have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion now for ſuch a great Man, who could ſee things in little, and in their prime.</note> and your Kingdoms in need of Coin.</p>
                  <p>Your Shipping, Traffick, and Mariner's decay'd.<note place="margin">For when this King ſet up for an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Peace, he laid up his Men of War, and left Merchandiſe to ſhift for it ſelf.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:37530:26"/>Whilſt your Majeſty's Neighbours without theſe means,<note place="margin">Whilſt this King ſang Lullaby to his Subjects, they ſlept on; but the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> were vigilant, and awake all this whilt; which makes us now ſleep the leſs, and (as it ſhould behove us) to think the more.</note> abound in Wealth, enlarge their Towns, encreaſe their Shipping, Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick, and Mariners, and find out ſuch Employment for their People, that they are all advantageous to their Common Wealth, only by ordaining commodious Conſtitutions in Merchandizing, and fulneſs of Trade in Manufactury.</p>
                  <p>God hath bleſs'd your Majeſty with incomparable Benefits of Copper,<note place="margin">P. 186.</note> Lead, Tyn, Iron, Alum, Copperas, Saffron, Fells, and divers other Native Commodities, to the number of about 100. and other Manufactures vendible, to the number of about 1000. beſides Corn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as alſo Wool, whereof much is ſhipp'd off,<note place="margin">☞</note> unwrought into Cloth, and Stuff; and ☞ Cloth, and Stuff tranſported undreſs'd,<note place="margin">☞</note> and undy'd, which doth employ near Fifty Thouſand People in Foreign Parts,<note place="margin">☞</note> whilſt you Majeſty's People want that Employment in <hi>England.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">☞</note> 
                     <note place="margin">And ſee, <hi>p. 191.</hi> and <hi>195.</hi> how many Millions this Nation hath loſt for want of following the full Trade of Manufacture and Fiſhery.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe Inconveniencies happen by Three Cauſes eſpecially.<note place="margin">P. 187.</note>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. The unprofitable courſe of Merchandiſe.</item>
                     <item>2. The want of full Manufacture.</item>
                     <item>III. The undervaluing of our Coin.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Our Merchant-Adventurers by over-trading upon Credit,<note place="margin">P. 188.</note> or by Money taken upon Exchange, whereby they loſe uſually 10 and 12 <hi>per Cent;</hi> and ſometimes 15, or 16, are forced to make Sale of their Cloths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at under-rates, to keep up their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, whereby Cloths, being the Jewel of the Land, are under va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued, and the Merchants in ſhort time eaten out.</p>
                  <p>The Weſt Countrey-Merchants,<note place="margin">P. 189.</note> that trade in Cloths to <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> do uſually employ their Servants (young Men of ſmall Experience) who by the Cunning of the <hi>French,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and Factors do now combine with the Aliens, as the Aliens then combin'd with one another, to <hi>out wit</hi> the Principals here.</note> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants are ſo entrapped—</p>
                  <p>— that when all Cuſtoms and Charges be accounted, their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhall hardly receive their Principal Money.</p>
                  <p>As for our returns out of <hi>France,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ditto.</note> their Silver and Gold is ſo highly rated,<note place="margin">☞</note> that our Merchants cannot bring it home but to great loſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:37530:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>Therefore the <hi>French</hi> Merchants ſet higher rates upon their Commodities, which we muſt either buy dear,<note place="margin">☜</note> or let our Money lie dead there a long time, until we can conveniently imploy the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore may it pleaſe your Majeſty to conſider theſe points following.<note place="margin">P. 202.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Whether it be not fit, that a <hi>State Merchant</hi> be ſettled in your Dominions, which may encounter the policies of Merchant Strangers, who now go beyond us in all profitable Merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whether it be not neceſſary,<note place="margin">☜</note> that our Native Commodities ſhould receive their full Manufacture by your own Subjects.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Whether it be not fit for your Majeſty preſently to raiſe your Coin to as high rates, as it is in the parts beyond Seas.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Whether it be not neceſſary,<note place="margin">We have been ſince too for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to cheat the World with our Fiſh, inſomuch that they have left us much upon that Account; and, as if the Fiſh themſelves had reſented the Injuries done to them, they have as much left us alſo, under the like Judgment which befell the Jews, <hi>Thy Fiſhers alſo ſhall mourn, and they that ſpread Nets upon the Water ſhall languiſh.</hi>
                     </note> that the great Sea buſineſs of Fiſhing be not forthwith ſet forward.</p>
                  <q>May it pleaſe your Majeſty,<note place="margin">P. 203.</note>
                  </q>
                  <p>I have the rather undergone the pains of looking into the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> becauſe I have heard them profeſs they hoped to get the whole Trade of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> into their hands.<note place="margin">And how near the <hi>French</hi> had got the Trade, and <hi>Holland</hi> into the Bargain, let them judge that beſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Advantage we have by the preſent War.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>French</hi> King hath been diſciplining a victorious,<note place="margin">Britannia Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guens, <hi>p.</hi> 207.</note> and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Army, and exhauſting us by his Trade, with a great addition of loſs by his Capers; and, at laſt, hath (as it were) forced a General Peace.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore, in order to our future Safety, it is indiſpenſibly,<note place="margin">276.</note> and ſpeedily neceſſary to improve, and regulate our Trade to the utmoſt.</p>
                  <p>And a compleat regulation of our Trade would render it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digiouſly beneficial; perhaps,<note place="margin">286.</note> more than all the Trade of <hi>Europe</hi> beſides, conſidering how our Advantages in Trade will reduce the Trade of our Neighbours, as ours does improve.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:37530:27"/>If our Trade had been regulated,<note place="margin">291.</note> the very <hi>Dutch</hi> would have forſaken thoſe Provinces for <hi>England,</hi> or if they had remained, they would have been Carriers for the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as they have been to the <hi>French,</hi> and will rather be ſo for the future.</p>
                  <p>The Trade of the World have long courted <hi>England,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 301.</note> but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with ſo much importunity, or with ſo much advantage as now.</p>
                  <p>This great Lady affecting Freedom and ſecurity hath no incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to continue under the Arbitrary Power of the <hi>French.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>With <hi>France</hi> ſhe hath reſided only as a Sojourner, but is ready to eſpouſe our Intereſt and Nation, and with her ſelf to beſtow upon us the Treaſure of the World.</p>
                  <p>But if we will ſtill continue inexorable and ſtubborn, things are grown to ſuch a <hi>Criſis,</hi> that we may have reaſon to fear, that this is the laſt time of asking.</p>
                  <p>And that ſhe may ſuddenly turn this kindneſs for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom into ſuch a fury, as we ſhall not be able to withſtand.</p>
                  <p>Shall we then embrace ſo advantageous overtures, or ſhall we proceed in our preſent Methods?</p>
                  <p>I ſhall leave it here to be computed,<note place="margin">P. 279.</note> how near a Million <hi>per An.</hi> our <hi>French</hi> over-balance hath been, ever ſince the Prohibition; not forgetting the courteſie of our Merchants, who hearing of the Prohibition, imported of <hi>French</hi> Goods to the value of about a Million.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Beſides thoſe fruitfull Iſlands,<note place="margin">Speed<hi>'s Chron.</hi> P. 1.</note> that diſperſedly are ſcattered about the Main, like to beautifull Pearl, that incompaſs a Diadem, the Iſle of <hi>Great Britain</hi> does raiſe itſelf firſt to our ſight, as to the body of <hi>that moſt famous and mighty Empire,</hi> whereof many other Kingdoms and Countries are Parcels and Members, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Almighty ſo ſet in the Main Ocean, as that She is thereby <hi>the High Admiral of the Seas, and the Terreſtrial Globe;</hi> So ſeated, as that She is worthily reputed, <hi>both the Garden of Pleaſure, and the Store-houſe of Profit;</hi> opening her Havens every way ſit to receive all Foreign Traffick, and to utter her own into all other parts; and therefore, <hi>as the Sovereign Lady and Empreſs of the reſt,</hi> deſerves our deſcription in the firſt place.</p>
                  <p>And Mr. <hi>Reynell</hi> ſaith thus of <hi>Jamaica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:37530:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>Jamaica</hi> is the place that will turn to a great Advantage to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> on many Accounts,<note place="margin">Engliſh Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, <hi>p.</hi> 83.</note> as by lying ſo near the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> of <hi>Pana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> and for ſeveral other Advantages which I ſhall not now mention. But the very Situation of the Iſland is extraordinary remarkable, and it was the greateſt Bleſſing imaginable that we left the Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize of <hi>Hiſpaniola</hi> and ſet on this Iſland; For if we had ſtudied an Age to fix in a place, where we might Center the richeſt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Trade of the <hi>Indies,</hi> here it muſt be. For <hi>Jamaica</hi> is Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated ſo well for Trade, or Conqueſt of the Main, if there be Occaſion, that no Iſland in the World lyes like it for Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, it being the Key of the <hi>Indies,</hi> and naturally the Seat of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and Empire. So that if they had but a Trade once with the <hi>Indies</hi> adjoyning, they have no way to avoid being the richeſt Colony in the <hi>Indies,</hi> it being wholly ſurrounded with the main Land, and Iſlands; lying in the very Belly of all Commerce in the In-land Sea of <hi>Porto Bell,</hi> which is in the heart of <hi>America,</hi> and near the <hi>Mexican</hi> Gulph, between <hi>Peru</hi> and <hi>Mexico,</hi> facing to the South and Weſt; the richeſt Continent in the World, from which not diſtant any where much above 100 Leagues. Againſt it on the North lie the two great Iſlands of <hi>Cuba</hi> and <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle behither Eaſtward are the <hi>Caribbee Iſlands,</hi> but this lieth in the midſt of all, as Queen of the <hi>Indian</hi> Iſles; and no Ship that comes from the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> but muſt paſs by one End of this Iſle, before they come to the Gulph of <hi>Florida,</hi> which place all Ships muſt paſs that come for <hi>Europe.</hi> And had we but a Trade with the <hi>Indies,</hi> ſo near Neighbours to us, we ſhould vend more Commodities than we could ſend them, and have in Exchange ſtore of Silver. 'Twere the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Intereſt alſo to let us have a free Trade, and ſhare with them of ſome few Port-Towns on the Continent, to maintain a Trade, and Neighbourlineſs between us; ſo ſhould we not endanger them, but equally defend the <hi>Indies</hi> with them, and they by our means have twice the Riches yearly come home to <hi>Spain</hi> that now they have.</p>
                  <p>Now (ſaith the ſame Author in his Preface) it is a very hard Caſe, if the Heavenly Bounty ſhall by Nature thus furniſh us with ſo great Aſſiſtances, and we ſhould not add to it, and give ſome Advance by our own Art and Induſtry; bringing in whatever Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Arts, Trades, or Husbandry, may be profitable to us.<note place="margin">☜</note> For doubtleſs we may Aggrandize our Trade to an ineſtimable Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, if we would our ſelves, and make our Territories as rich and populous as we pleaſe, under ſo Glorious a King, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment as we have; had we but that publick Spirit as we ought,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:37530:28"/>and gave Countenance to brave Actions, and induſtrious Men; and minded the Buſineſs of Trade and Populacy, as much as we do Pleaſures, and Luxuries. And if we were but Induſtrious no Nation can exceed us, in a home or foreign Trade; and for fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Trade <hi>England</hi> lies ſo ſurrounded with our Neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that it ſeems deſigned for all manner of Riches, and <hi>for the Seat of the Empire.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>The Kingdom of Heaven (ſaith my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> in his <hi>Summa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Treatiſe to King</hi> James <hi>the Firſt, touching the enlarging of the Bounds of Empire</hi>) is compared not to an Acorn, or Nut, but to a Grain of Muſtard-ſeed, which is one of the leaſt Grains, but hath in it a Property and Spirit, haſtily to get up, and ſpread it ſelf. So are there Kingdoms and States in Compaſs, and Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, very great, and yet not ſo apt to enlarge their Bounds, or Command, and ſome on the other hand, that have but a ſmall Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſion of Stem, and yet are apt to be the Foundation of great Monarchies.</p>
                  <p>And (in his <hi>Conſiderations touching a War with</hi> Spain) He ſaith to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, then Prince. <hi>Your Highneſs hath an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Name; it was a</hi> Charles <hi>that brought the Empire firſt into</hi> France, <hi>a</hi> Charles <hi>that brought it first into</hi> Spain, <hi>and why ſhould not</hi> Great Britain <hi>have it's Turn?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>England</hi> being by Nature the <hi>Emporium</hi> of the World, is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the fitteſt Seat for the <hi>Empire of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe;</hi> as well as that of <hi>the Ocean;</hi> which (as my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> ſaith,) <hi>Is the principal Dowry of the Kingdom of</hi> Great Britain, <hi>and is of great Import to us, becauſe moſt of the Kingdoms of</hi> Europe, <hi>are not merely in Land, but girt with the Sea moſt part of their Compaſs; and becauſe the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and Wealth of both</hi> Indies <hi>ſeems in a great part but an Acceſſary to the Command of the Sea;</hi> and what the Command of the Sea is, we may ſee by the Succeſs of the Battle of <hi>Lepanto,</hi> which put a Ring into the Noſe of the <hi>Turk;</hi> by that of the Battel of <hi>Actium,</hi> That decided the Empire of the World, and by that of our laſt Sea Fight with the <hi>French.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>And as we have a Country ſo fit for <hi>the Seat of the Empire</hi> ſo have we a King as fit to be Supream Head and Governour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:37530:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>A Man of War from his Touch up,</hi> and one that is Maſter of the Four Miſtriſs and Moral Vertues, <hi>Prudence, Juſtice, Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> and <hi>Temperance,</hi> ſuch a one, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſeems to have Propheſied of, when he told the World, That <hi>the Power of the Earth was in the hands of the Lord, and he would in due time ſet over it one that is profitable And ſince we have ſuch a King,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>Goliah</hi> to fight our Battels for us in Perſon (a Man after ſuch a Countries own Heart) we cannot but ſollicite Heaven, and all the Hoſt thereof to ſend him the Succeſs of <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>the Hearts of his Friends,</hi> as well as <hi>the Necks of the Enemies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For God hath been pleaſed in great Pity,<note place="margin">His Grace the late Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury, 4</hi> Vol. of Serm. p. <hi>78, 79.</hi>
                     </note> to this ſinful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Nation, to raiſe him on purpoſe for it, and to that End did in his All-wiſe Providence, lay the Foundation of our Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, in that Auſpicious Match which was concluded here in <hi>England.</hi> This is that moſt Illuſtrious Houſe of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> and <hi>Orange,</hi> which God hath ſo highly honoured above all the Families of the Earth, to give a Check to the two great Aſpiring Monarchs of the Weſt, and bold Attempters upon the Liberty of <hi>Europe.</hi> To the one in the laſt Age, and to the other in the preſent. As if the Princes of this Valiant and Victorious Line, had been of the Race of <hi>Hercules,</hi> born to reſcue mankind from Oppreſſion, and to quel Monſters.</p>
                  <p>The Houſe of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> is without Contradiction,<note place="margin">Lives of the Princes of <hi>Orange,</hi> p. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </note> one of the greateſt and ancienteſt in all <hi>Germany.</hi> For beſides its high Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, the number of its Branches, and the Honour of giving an Emperor near Four hundred Years ſince, it has this particular Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, to have continued ten entire Ages, and to boaſt with the State of <hi>Venice</hi> (as a Learned man ſaith) that it's Government is founded upon a Baſis of a Thouſand years ſtanding.</p>
                  <p>No Age of all Antiquity has produced a more extraordinary Man, than <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Speaking of the Life of <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> Founder of the Common-Wealth of the united Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces in the <hi>Neitherlands,</hi> p. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> Examine all the Heroes of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and all thoſe great Men who lived ſince that admirable Hiſtorian, and it 'twill be Difficult to find any upon Record, who poſſeſſed more eminently all thoſe Vertues, and good Qualities that enter into the Compoſition of a brave Man.</p>
                  <p>The Victories and Conqueſt of <hi>Allexander,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> do not ſo much deſerve our Admiration, the firſt was Maſter of all <hi>Greece,</hi> and at the Head of a Warlike and well diſciplin'd Army, the other abſolutely Commanded half the <hi>Roman</hi> Legions, who governed all the World. With theſe great Forces and Advantages, they enter'd upon the Stage, made their firſt Victories the Forerunners to the next, purſued their Blow, and the one overthrew the Empire of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> and the other the <hi>Roman</hi> Commonwealth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:37530:29"/>But Prince <hi>William</hi> had equall'd the Glory of theſe great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, by Attacking the formidable Power of King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> without any Army or Forces, and by maintaining himſelf many Years againſt him. His Courage was always greater than his Misfortunes; and when all the World thought him ruin'd, and he was driven out of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> he entred them again immediately at the Head of a new Army; and, by his great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, laid the Foundation of their Common Wealth.</p>
                  <q>A Prince the beſt qualified for a Throne,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>New State of</hi> England, <hi>p. 122,</hi> &amp;c. Speaking of his preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</note> being great without Pride, true to his Word, wiſe in his Deliberations, ſecret in his Councils, generous in his Attempts, undaunted in Danger, Valiant without Cruelty; who loves Juſtice with Moderation, Government without Tyranny, Religion without Perſecution, and Devotion without Hypocriſie, or Superſtition. A Prince, undaunted under all Events, never puffed up with Succeſs, or diſheartned with Hardſhips, and Misfortunes; always the ſame, tho' under various Circumſtances; which is the true Symptom of a Great Soul.</q>
                  <p>This generous Temper of the King is ſuitable to his Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; being deſcended from an ancient and illuſtrious Family, which ſeems to have been appointed by Providence, ever ſince the Reformation, for <hi>the Preſervation of God's Church,</hi> and <hi>a Check to Tyranny.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>And this Great King, and that Country, which is ſo honoured and happy with him, calls to my mind Mr. <hi>Quarles</hi>'s Colloquy with his Soul.</p>
                  <p>So now,<note place="margin">Boanerges <hi>and St.</hi> Barnabas, p. 109.</note> my Soul, thy Happineſs is entail'd, and thy Illuſtrious Name ſhall live in thy ſucceeding Generations; Thy Dwelling is eſtabliſh'd in the Fat of all the Land; The beſt of all the Land is thine, and thou art planted in the beſt of Lands; A Land, whoſe Conſtitutions make the beſt of Government; which Government is ſtrengthened with the beſt of Laws;<note place="margin">Good Laws, but ill execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> A Land of Strength and of Plenty; A Land whoſe Beauty hath ſurprized the ambitious Hearts of Foreign Princes; A Land whoſe native Plenty makes her the World's Exchange, ſupplying others, and able to ſubſiſt without ſupply from them; That hath no miſery, but what is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated from that blindneſs, which cannot ſee her own Felicity; A Land that flows with Milk, and Honey, and, in brief, wants no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to deſerve the Title of a Paradiſe; The Curb of <hi>Spain,</hi> the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37530:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>Pride of <hi>Germany,</hi> the Aid of <hi>Belgia,</hi> the Scourge of <hi>France,</hi> the Queen of Nations, and the Empeteſs of the World.</p>
                  <p>And being (as he elegantly goes on) <hi>begirt with Walls, whoſe Bullder was the hand Heaven, whereon there daily rides a Navy Royal, whoſe unconquerable Power proclaims her Prince invincible, and whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers ſad deſpair into the fainting heart of Foreign Majeſty.</hi> Het Prince might ſay to us concerning the Empire, as <hi>Joſhua</hi> did to the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> concerning <hi>Canaan, How long are you ſlack to go to poſſeſs the Land, which the Lord God of your Fathers hath given you?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>But there are three principal things, which in <hi>Martial</hi> as well as civil Policy, are firſt to be better regarded than they are, <hi>viz.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Trade, and Juſtice.</p>
                  <p>By Religion, I mean, that which <hi>ſo effectually provides for all thoſe advantages to Mankind,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dec. <hi>of</hi> Piet. P. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>which the wiſeſt of Men's Laws have in vain attempted: That Chriſt came to introduce Religion, which conſults not only the co-eternal Salvation of Men's Souls,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sermon on</hi> Luke 9. v. 55, 56.</note> 
                     <hi>but their temporal peace and ſecurity, their comfort and happineſs in this World; and</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Fleetwood</hi> ſaith in his Sermon againſt Clipping) <hi>if there appears but little Chriſtianity in ſuch a Sermon, it will be to ſuch as conſider not how great a Part, Juſtice, and Honeſty, and fair and righteous dealing make up of Divine Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">In his Rules for preſerving the State.</note> that <hi>The firſt and principal Rule of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy is the practice of Religion;</hi> and the Cardinal <hi>de Richlien</hi> in his Political Teſtament, calls it <hi>the Eſtabliſhment of the Reign of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By Trade, I mean, ſuch a free and full manufactured Trade, which the <hi>Romans</hi> by all poſſible Arts aſcended to, e'er they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended to the heighth of Empire, whoſe Steps the <hi>French</hi> lately endeavoured to follow by all means imaginable, and for the ſelf ſame end, and not ſuch a Trade for which this Nation became ſo renowned, as <hi>Glaucus</hi> is in <hi>Homer</hi> for changing Armour with <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medes,</hi> with ſuch palpable diſadvantage that Proverbs came of it.</p>
                  <p>And by Juſtice. I mean, not <hi>ſummum jus ſumma Injuria,</hi> but * <hi>the Policy of Engliſh Government,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prol. <hi>to</hi> Hiſt. <hi>Diſc.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>which ſo far as is praiſe worthy is all one with Divine Providence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Such <hi>Juſtice</hi> as honours the <hi>Religion,</hi> and advanceth the <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Trade</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> that is, ſuch <hi>Righteous Judgment</hi> as God Almighty himſelf at firſt commanded, <hi>Judges and Officers ſhalt thou make, ſuch as ſhall judge the People with righteous Judgment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:37530:30"/>The <hi>ſummum jus</hi> of this Nation is of <hi>Humnut,</hi> and, I think, of <hi>Norman Inſtitution;</hi> and it is yet known, and perhaps, may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be forgotten, that <hi>from the fury of the</hi> Normans, was added to our Anceſtor's Common-Prayer, againſt <hi>Plague, Peſtilence, and Famine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour (<hi>Jehu</hi> like) drove out the Laws of King <hi>Edward</hi> then in uſe,<note place="margin">Bak. <hi>Chron.</hi> Pag 28.</note> contrary to his Coronation Oath, and in their ſtead, brought in the Laws of <hi>Normandy,</hi> commanding them to be written in <hi>French;</hi> as alſo, that all Cauſes ſhould be pleaded, and all matters of Form diſputized in <hi>French,</hi> upon a pretence to dignifie the <hi>French</hi> Tongue; but it was with a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to intrap Men through the Ignorance of the Language, as indeed it did.</p>
                  <p>And whereas before,<note place="margin">P. 29.</note> the Biſhop and the Aldermen were the abſolute Judges to determine all buſineſs in every Shire, and the Biſhop in many Caſes ſhared in the benefit of the Mulct with the King, he confined the Clergy within the Province of their own Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction.</p>
                  <p>And whereas the Cauſes of the Kingdom were before determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in every Shire, and by a Law of King <hi>Edward</hi> in a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle held Monthly in every Hundred, he ordained that four times in the Year, for certain days, the ſame buſineſs ſhould be determin'd in ſuch places as he ſhould appoint: And finally he ordained his Council of State, his Chancery, and his Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>But <hi>Edward</hi> III. the moſt Generous, Magnanimous, Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and Heroick Prince of all his Race and Predeceſſors, having due regard to <hi>Religion, Grievances, Trade,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to Martial Policy and Diſcipline, ordain'd, and in ſome Reſpects contrary to his Intereſts,</p>
                  <p>That no <hi>Peter pence</hi> ſhould be paid to the <hi>Pope of Rome,</hi> that <hi>(the Service of God being perfect freedom)</hi> his People of <hi>England</hi> might ſay their <hi>Pater-noſter</hi> without paying the <hi>Penny</hi> for it.</p>
                  <p>That no Wool growing within this Realm ſhould be tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but that it ſhould be made into Cloth in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the <hi>Walloons</hi> ſhould be permitted to Live, Work, and Trade amongſt us, and be naturalized againſt the Act.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:37530:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> which we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> before in <hi>French,</hi> ſhould be made in <hi>Engliſh</hi> that the Cliche might underſtand the Courſe of the Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A bleſſed Act</hi> (ſaith my Author) <hi>and worthy ſo great a King,</hi> who if he could thereby render it alſo perſpicuous, plain, eaſie, and ſhort, it would be a Work of Eternal Honour to him, and everlaſting Intereſt to the Nation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>But our People being <hi>a Rebellious People,</hi> and undeſerving of ſuch excellent Princes, as <hi>Edward</hi> III. <hi>Henry</hi> V. and Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> by the Providence of God <hi>took from them,</hi> as it did from <hi>Judah and Jeruſalem, the Mighty Man, the Man of War, the Prudent, the Elegant Orater, the Cunning Artificer, the Counſellor, and the Judge, ſo that the People were oppreſſed every one by another, and every one by his Neighbour, and their Tongues and their doings being againſt the Lord, the Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>d of their own hands was given unto them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>Yet ſtill the Providence of God <hi>eſpouſing us,</hi> as it did the <hi>Jews,</hi> or rather (as Dr. <hi>So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ſaith) <hi>as</hi> Socrates <hi>eſpouſed</hi> Xantippe <hi>to exerciſe his Patience without;</hi> He hath now ſent us <hi>a King of Kings,</hi> who at his firſt coming to the Imperial Crown of <hi>England,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed (againſt his own preſent and private Intereſt) <hi>the Balance of the Trade of this Nation,</hi> well knowing the nature of this Kingdom, for advantageous Commerce, and that <hi>a good Father of his Country, as well as of his Family, will be</hi> Vendacem, <hi>and not</hi> Em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cem, as Sir <hi>Robert Cotton</hi> ſaith of him.</p>
                  <p>And indeed ſo much, and much more were (in Civil Opinion and Martial Policy) to be expected from ſuch a Puiſſant Prince, whoſe Godly, Generous, Noble, and Reſolute Race, eſpecially from <hi>William</hi> I. to <hi>William</hi> III. hath been a ſucceſsful Series of eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Sincerity towards <hi>Religion, Grievances, Trade,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>His late Princely and Pious Conſort (now a <hi>Queen of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi>) was an enamoured Lover of Religion and Juſtice, to the eternal Honour of her Majeſtick and Immortal Memory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:37530:31"/>And ſince ſhe had laid ſuch excellent Deſigns for both, I hope the Omnipotence of God Almighty will ſee them finished, by means of her Royal and moſt excellent Survivor, <hi>for his Name ſake.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>The Seat of Government is upheld by the <hi>Two great Pillar,</hi> thereof,<note place="margin">Rawl <hi>Remark.</hi> P. 153.</note> 
                     <hi>Civil Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Martial Policy,</hi> which were framed out of the Husbandry, Merchandiſe, and Gentry of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
                  <p>They ſay, that the goodlieſt <hi>Cedars,</hi> which grow on the high Mountains of <hi>Libanus,</hi> thruſt their Roots between the Cliffs of hard Rocks, the better to bear themſelves againſt the ſtrong Storms that blow there.</p>
                  <p>As Nature hath inſtructed thoſe Kings of Trees, ſo hath Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon taught the Kings of Men to root themſelves in the hardy Hearts of their faithful Subjects.</p>
                  <p>And as thoſe Kings of Trees have large Tops, ſo have the Kings of Men large Crowns.</p>
                  <p>Whereof as the firſt would ſoon be broken from their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, were they not under-born by many Branches; ſo would the other eaſily totter, were they not faſtned in their Heads ☞ with ſtrong Chains of <hi>Civil Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Martial Diſcipline.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">P. 154.</note> For the Adminiſtration of the Firſt, even God himſelf hath given direction: <hi>Judges and Officers ſhalt thou make, which ſhall Judge the People with righteous Judgment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The ſecond is grounded on the firſt Laws of the World and Nature, That <hi>Force is to be repall'd by Force.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yea <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the <hi>20th.</hi> of <hi>Exodus,</hi> and elſewhere, hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd us many Laws, and Policies of War.</p>
                  <p>☞ But as we have heard of the Neglect and Abuſe in both; ſo have we heard of the Decline and Ruin of many Kingdoms and States before our days.</p>
                  <p>For that Policy hath ever yet prevail'd (though it hath ſerved for a ſhort ſeaſon) where the Counterfeit hath been ſold for ☞ the Natural, and the outward Show and <hi>Formality</hi> for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:37530:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>Of the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> IV. the Wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> of that Age wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>, That he uſed but the Name of Juſtice, and good Rule, and Order, being more learned in the Law, than in doing Right;☜ and that he had, by far, more Knowledge and Law, than Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="section">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>But we will forbear, for a while, to ſtretch this firſt String of Civil Juſtice: For in reſpect of the firſt ſort of Men,<note place="margin">Husband-men, <hi>P. 156.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>viz.</hi> of thoſe that live by their own Labour, they have never been diſpleaſed, where they have been ſuffer'd to enjoy the Fruit of their own Travels: <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> is all wherein they ſeek their Certainty and Protection.<note place="margin">But <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> is now a long time a trying, when the Defendant runs from one Court to another, and at laſt betakes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the <hi>Reſuge,</hi> or <hi>Aſſylum,</hi> of <hi>Summum Judicium.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>True it is, That they are the Fruit. Trees of the Land,<note place="margin">P. 156.</note> which☜ <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> commanded <hi>to be</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">And here let me note (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the common Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Nation) that the Sea and Land, I mean the <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>Navigation,</hi> ought to be Taxed leſs, and the <hi>Faſeful</hi> and <hi>Idle</hi> more than any other things in the Kingdom. To Tax the Land ever-much, and Navigation in never ſo little, is to ſtop the very Vitals of Trade, and by conſequence to decreaſe our Soldiers, Sea-men, and Treaſure. The Sea-men and Shipping (as they are the Walls of our Nation) muſt be encouraged by all means imaginable. And the Land-men muſt have Stock by them, to improve their Lands and their Manſions, and to keep Houſes of Hoſpitality: Which if they do not, they ruin the poor Labourers, by not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying them. And if they do employ them, and keep Houſes of Hoſpitality, they will ruin themſelves, if their Eſtates be over-taxed. So that the Vices, the Luxury, and Gallantry of the Nation, ought to be moſtly conſider'd in that reſpect.</note> 
                     <hi>ſpared.</hi> They gather Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and hardly enjoy the Wax; and break the Ground with great Labour, giving the beſt of their Grain to the Eaſeful and Idle.</p>
                  <p>For the ſecond ſort, which are the Merchants;<note place="margin">Merchants. <hi>P. 157.</hi>
                     </note> as the firſt feed the Kingdom, ſo do theſe enrich it; yea, their Trades, eſpecially thoſe which are forcible, are not the leaſt part of our <hi>Martial Policy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And to do them right, they have, in all Ages and Times, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted the Kings of this Land, not only with great Summs of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, but with great Fleets of Ships, in all their Enterprizes beyond Sea.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:37530:32"/>The third ſort, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>y of <hi>England,</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the loweſt Ground, and thereby ſubject to the biting of every Beaſt; nor in the higheſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and thereby in danger to be torn with Tempeſts; but in the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys between both, have their part in the inferiour Juſtice, and being ſpread over all, are the Garriſons of good Order through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Realm.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="section">
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <p>In the Situation of Countries and Cities,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>P. 142.</hi> Situation for Safety and Plenty.</note> there is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd a Place of Safety by ſome natural Strength, commodiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for Navigation and Conduct, for the obtaining of plenty of all good Things, for the Suſtenance and Comfort of Man's Life, and to draw Trade and Intercourſe of other Nations.</p>
                  <p>In former times,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>P. 14.</hi> Multitude of Inhabitants.</note> great Nations, Kings, and Potentates, have endured ſharp Conflicts, and held it high Policy, by all means, to enor eaſe their Cities by multitudes of inhabitants.</p>
                  <p>☞ And to this End, the <hi>Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ever furniſhed themſelves with Strength, and Power, to make their Neighbour-People of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, willing to draw themſelves to dwell at <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Romulus,</hi> after a mighty Fight with the <hi>Sabines,</hi> condeſcended to Peace, upon condition, that their King ſhould come with all their People to dwell at <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame Courſe held <hi>Tamberlane</hi> the Great, whereby he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged the Great <hi>Samarcanda.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the <hi>Ottomans,</hi> to make the City <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> rich and great, brought to it many Thouſand Families, eſpecially Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers out of the ſubdued Cities.</p>
                  <p>Religion,<note place="margin">Religion.</note> which is of ſuch Force and Might, to amplifie Cities, and Dominions, and of ſuch Attractive Vertue, to repleniſh the ſame with People, and Wealth, and to have them in due Obedience, as ☞ none can be more: For without Adoration of ſome Deity, no Common-wealth can ſubſiſt. Witneſs <hi>Jeruſalem, Rome, Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> and all other Cities, that have been famous for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion, and Divine Worſhip.</p>
                  <p>Court of Juſtice with due Execution of the ſame,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Juſtice.</hi> P. 147.</note> in a City, do much enable, enlarge, and enrich it.</p>
                  <p>☞ For it faſtneth a great liking in a City to vertuous Men, and ſuch as be wealthy, that therein they may be free from the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence and Oppreſſions of covetous and wicked Men, and there will be rather reſort thither, to inhabit or traffick there, as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion may miniſter unto them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:37530:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> have C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> will repair thither,<note place="margin">☜</note> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e they may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to find Indgment and Juſtice, duely executed, where by a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> City muſt needs be enriched and enlarged.</p>
                  <p>For our Lives and Fortunes, and all that ever we have in the<note place="margin">☜</note> World, is in the Hands of Juſtice.</p>
                  <p>So that if Justice be not duly and truly, and without delay,<note place="margin">☜</note>adminiſtred amongſt Men, in vain is there any Society and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce.<note place="margin">☜</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="section">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>Put the Caſe, as it is mine, That I had been a Factor at <hi>Zant,</hi> and a Merchant in <hi>London</hi> ſhould give me a Commiſſion to lay out 4000 <hi>l.</hi> for him on a Cargoe of Currans, and to re-imburſe my ſelf on him by way of <hi>Venice.</hi> I lay out the 4000 <hi>l.</hi> and lade the Ship, and when the Ship is gone from <hi>Zant,</hi> the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant in <hi>London</hi> writes to his Factor at <hi>Venice,</hi> not to accept or pay any Bills. What muſt I do then? why, I muſt even leave my Profeſſion at <hi>Zant,</hi> and come home to follow a Law-ſuit in <hi>England.</hi> And what follows then? That, Sir <hi>Joſiah Child</hi> tells you.</p>
                  <p>The want of a Court-Merchant in <hi>England,</hi> is,<note place="margin">New Diſc. of Trade, <hi>p.</hi> 112, 113, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> and ever hath been a great Barr to the Progreſs and Grandeur of the Trade of this Kingdom: As for inſtance,</p>
                  <p n="1">I. A Merchant, happen to have differences with Maſters and Owners of Ships upon Charter-parties, and Accounts beyond Sea, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Suit is commonly firſt commenc'd in the Admiral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-Court; where, after tedious Attendance, and vaſt Expences pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably, juſt before the Cauſe ſhould come to determination, it is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther removed into the Delegates, where it may hang in ſuſpence, until the Plaintiff and Defendant have empty Purſes and Gray-heads.</p>
                  <p>Or elſe, becauſe moſt Contracts for Maritime Affairs are made upon the Land, and moſt Accidents happen in ſome Rivers, or Harbours here, or beyond Sea, are not in <hi>Alto Mare,</hi> the Defendant brings his Writ of Prohibition, and removes the Cauſe into his Majeſties Court of King's-Bench.</p>
                  <p>Where after great Expences of Time and Money, it is well if we can make our own Counſel (being common Lawyers) under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand one half of our Caſe, we being amongſt Strangers, as in a Foreign Country; our Language ſtrange to them, and theirs as ſtrange to us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:37530:33"/>After all, no Atteſtations of Foreign No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ies, nor other Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Inſtruments from beyond the Seas being Evidences at Law, and the Accounts depending, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> perhaps of 100 or more ſeveral Articles, which are as ſo many Iſſues at Law, the Cauſe muſt come into Chancery.</p>
                  <p>Where, after many Years tedious Travels to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> with black Boxes, and green Baggs, when the Plaintiff and Defendant have tired their Bodies, diſtracted their Brains, and conſumed their Eſtates, the Cauſe, if ever it be ended, is commonly reſerred to Merchants, ending miſerably, where it might have had at firſt a happy Iſſue, if it had been begun a-right.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Cloſe.</head>
               <p>Theſe things being ſo great a Diſhonour to ſo great a King, and ſo great a Diſintereſt to ſo great a Country, do highly deſerve the Conſideration of both Houſes of Parliament. To whom I humbly ſubmit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:37530:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HAD</hi> it not been for the Diverſions of Law, and ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervening Accidents, this Eſſay or Collection had come ſooner out, to ſave ſome Pains that have been taken, <hi>to regula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the Coin and Commerce of the Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed, if our <hi>Commerce</hi> be not regulated, together with our <hi>Coin,</hi> and both ſupported by <hi>pure Religion, and undefiled Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> we may ſtamp our <hi>New Coin</hi> with this Superſcription, <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ius Bellum Pace Dubia,</hi> as the Dutch coin'd ſome Money with the ſame <hi>Motto,</hi> when the Treaty of Peace at <hi>Breda</hi> was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>French,</hi> having ſtill by them the true <hi>Ways and Means</hi> to gain the <hi>Over-balance of Trade,</hi> in time of Peace, and the moſt excellent Execution of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> (without which, there is little <hi>Martial-policy,</hi> and <hi>in vain is there any Society, and Commerce,</hi>) they, being <hi>very wiſe</hi> (like the <hi>Tyrians</hi>) will <hi>heap up Silver like the Duſt, and Gold like the Mire in the Streets,</hi> whilſt we <hi>caſt away care,</hi> and live like <hi>the — People that dwell at</hi> Sechem.</p>
               <p>But <hi>(nothing hurting the Engliſh Nature more than much quiet and peace)</hi> if we <hi>carry on that vigorous War againſt</hi> France (which his Majeſty hath begun) with <hi>Prudence, Juſtice, Fortitude, and Temperance,</hi> we may <hi>ſmite their Power in the Sea, and they ſhall be devoured by Fire.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>IN the <hi>the Votes of the Houſe of Commons,</hi> Martis 12 Die Martij 1694. I find the following Reſolutions of the Committee, which, it ſeems, were not agreed to by the whole Houſe.</p>
               <p>Reſolved, <hi>That it is the opinion of this Committee, That ten hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Thouſand Pounds is a ſufficient Summ, to make good the Deficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the preſent clipt Coin of this Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>our Silver is turn'd</hi> ſo much into Mixed-Metal,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> and <hi>Droſs</hi>-Money; that, if Six Millions be neceſſary to circulate, One Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, (with all Submiſſion) I think it will not be enough <hi>to make good the deficiency</hi> that will be be found, for carrying on the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:37530:34"/>of the Kingdom. Wherefore (for the preſent) until we can bring in more Bullion, by the over balance of Trade, ſome other Metal ſhould, <hi>with an E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be Milled, that the Charge ſhould prevent all practice of falſe Play.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>To the third, fourth, fifth and ſixth Reſolution, <hi>That the Crown and Half Crown, hereafter to be Coth'd, ſhall be of the preſent Weight and Fineneſs— That the Crown piece ſhould go for Five Shillings Six-pence,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>That the preſent Mill'd Crown piece go for Five Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings Six-pence,</hi> &amp;c. I humbly anſwer:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That it would be for the Honour of the King, (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in for the Intereſt of the Country,) to have all the Money new Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and Mill'd, with his Majeſty's <hi>Image, and Superſcription;</hi> which Honour his Majeſty moſt highly merits; foraſmuch as his Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Care for the Commonwealth of the Kingdom, hath (againſt his own preſent Intereſt, and in ſuch a time of War) ecommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his Parliament <hi>the Balance of Trade;</hi> which is the principal Means to bring in <hi>Bullion</hi> and <hi>Plate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That, to carry on our Commerce with the more eaſe, we ſhould (I humbly think, as in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> 3) Coin our Money for conveniency.</p>
               <p>And, it would be (with ſubmiſſion) for the greater conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, and the eaſier, and better keeping of all Accompts, that our Crown-piece ſhould paſs but for a Crown; and that our new Coin ſhould be (as near as poſſible, reſpecting the charge of Coinage) <hi>as much in Money, as in Maſs.</hi> For we may (if we are not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our ſelves, and to the good Nature of our Nation) keep it from <hi>Exportation, and the Melting-Pot,</hi> by <hi>the over-balance of Trade;</hi> which is alſo the beſt Means to maintain a <hi>Vigorou, War.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>Reſolved, <hi>That it is the Opinion of this Committee, That it be Penal on all ſuch Perſons on whom Clippings are found.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that may ſometimes fall hard on ſome innocent People,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> for lately one Mr. <hi>Jarvis,</hi> a Tobacconiſt on <hi>Cock Hill,</hi> having ſound out a Thief that ſtole ſome Tobacco from him, the ſaid Thief, or ſome other Body for him, convey'd a parcel of Clippings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:37530:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>his Houſe; for which his Wife was committed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and was put to great Trouble, and Charge, before the could be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from thence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>Reſolved, <hi>That it is the Opinion of this Committee, That it be Penal on ſuch Perſons as ſhall Import any Clipt, or Counterfet Money.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I believe we have had as many Guinea's, and as much Clipt,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> Mix'd, and Droſs Money Imported upon us, as doth now circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late in the Nation. And to prevent ſuch Importation for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the one half, upon diſcovery thereof, ſhould go to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former, and the other to the King: For when an Act is juſt and good, they that inform in favour thereof, ſhould not loſe any Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit by ſcandalous Titles, or Opinion, but ſhould receive all En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement imaginable. When <hi>Rome</hi> was in a riſing condition, thoſe that Informed in her favour, were looked on as Men of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; but as ſhe went to ruin, and was expoſed by the Soldiers, (who ſhould preſerve her) to the <hi>Sale of who gave moſt,</hi> the Informers were looked upon to be only famous for Infamy, as they are now in other declining Countries.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>Reſolved, <hi>That it is the Opinion of this Committee, That it be Penal on any Perſon to Export Engliſh Bullion; and the proof to lie on the Exporter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I was extreamly glad when I read this Reſolution; for it will, by ſome kind of neceſſity, put us upon gaining the <hi>over balance of Trade;</hi> which is the only thing (next to <hi>Religion and Justice</hi>) which we want to gain <hi>the Empire of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi> as well as that <hi>of the Ocean</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Religion</hi> in <hi>Britain</hi> hath hitherto been, for the moſt part,<note place="margin">Hiſt. Diſc.</note> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by immediate Influence from Heaven.</p>
               <p>And the way of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Gentleneſs,</hi> hath had more Force in <hi>Britain</hi> than Arms.</p>
               <p>Under the wiſe Government of <hi>Aurelius</hi> the Emperour, mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Throne, crowned <hi>Lucius,</hi> firſt of all Kings, with the Royal Title of a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>And he was not ſo much a Vaſſal, as a Friend, and Ally to the <hi>Romans:</hi> And, perceiving the Empire to be paſt Noon, and their Lieutenants to comply with the Chriſtians, began to provide for
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:37530:35"/>future Generations; and, according to the Two grand Defects of <hi>Religion, and Juſtice,</hi> applyed himſelf to the eſtabliſhment of both.</p>
               <p>Which Act of <hi>Lucius,</hi> ſo advanced him in the Opinion of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that they knew not when they had ſaid enough of him.</p>
               <p>Whereas before, <hi>Britain</hi> was become <hi>a Glut of Wickedneſs, and a Burden that God would endure no longer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Kingdoms of Chriſtendom, now in being, had their riſing from the fall of <hi>Rome;</hi> and <hi>Vortigern</hi> (a Native of this Iſle), firſt eſtabliſhed here a free Kingdom, four hundred and fifty Years after Chriſt, and ſo left it to the <hi>Saxons.</hi> So <hi>England</hi> hath a great Precedency, in reſpect of the Antiquity of the Kingdom, which (as <hi>Beda</hi> obſerves) was always a <hi>Monarch</hi> in a <hi>Heptarchy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So it hath the Precedency likewiſe in reſpect of the Antiquity of the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joſeph of Arimathea</hi> planted the Chriſtian Religion, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the Paſſion of Chriſt, in this Realm.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> (one of them mentioned by St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dorotheus.</note> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.) was <hi>Epiſc. Britannorum;</hi> and likewiſe <hi>Simon Zelotes;</hi> yea, St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, as <hi>Theodoretus</hi> doth teſtifie.</p>
               <p>The firſt Chriſtian King in <hi>Europe,</hi> was <hi>Lucius Surius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the firſt that ever advanced the Papacy of <hi>Rome,</hi> was the Emperour <hi>Constantine,</hi> born at <hi>York.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, King of <hi>England,</hi> was (<hi>Anno</hi> 1338) crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Emperour, <hi>Vicarius Perpetuus Imperii.</hi> And <hi>William</hi> the Third, King of <hi>England,</hi> may be the greateſt Emperour that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was, if we are not wanting to him, when he is not to us.</p>
               <p>This Kingdom is held of God alone,<note place="margin">Cottoni Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huma, <hi>p.</hi> 87. <hi>Hiſt. Diſc. p.</hi> 3.</note> acknowledging no Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour.</p>
               <p>It was long before the Son of God was enwombed; and whilſt, as yet, Providence ſeem'd to cloſe only with the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation, and to hover over it, as a choice pick'd Place from all the Earth, that, with a gracious Eye, ſurveying the forſaken condition of all other Nations, it glanced on this Iſland. Both Thoughts and Words reflected on <hi>Iſles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa 42.4.31.3.60.4.66.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſles of the Gentiles, Iſles afar off;</hi> as if amongſt them the Lord of all the Earth had found out ſome place, that ſhould be to him, as the Gem of the Ring of this terreſtrial Globe.</p>
               <p>And if the ways of future Providence may be looked upon as a Gloſs of thoſe Prophecies, we muſt confeſs, that this Iſland was conceiv'd in the Womb thereof, long before it was manifeſted to the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:37530:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>No ſooner was the Scepter departed from <hi>Judah,</hi> but both it, and the Law-giver, came hither, as if we were the only <hi>White</hi> that was in God's Aim.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>VII</head>
               <p>And ſhall we, after all this (for the ſake of Self-intereſt) be any ways wanting to <hi>Albion,</hi> which God hath ſo highly honoured, and ſo bountifully bleſs'd above all the Kingdoms in the World?</p>
               <p>No, ſure; for there is nothing expected from our Gratitude to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and our Duty towards the Nation, but what the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Repreſentatives thereof may make practicable, by means of their principal Commitees of <hi>Religion, Grievances, Trade, and Juſtice;</hi> and the Power they have of ſending for <hi>Perſons, Papers and Records.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>And ſince they are as deeply engaged, as they are highly concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to regulate the Coin of the Kingdom, and to <hi>turn</hi> our <hi>Droſs into Silver</hi> again, I hope they will raiſe no ſmall Fund, or Sum of Money for it,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In a printed Paper, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> Reaſons for not laying any farther Impoſitions upon Coals, <hi>there is this Particular:</hi> Which, in things of Choice and Luxury, may be tolerable; but, in Caſes of Neceſſity, muſt be extream grievous, eſpecially to many Trades-men.</note> out of the Cauſes, and Effects of Extravagancy, and Covetouſneſs. I mean, ſuch Extravagancies, for the moſt part, as promote exceſſive and conſumptive Importations.</p>
               <p>And ſuch Covetouſneſs as makes (againſt the Laws of God, and the World) Twelve, and ſometimes Twenty <hi>per Cent,</hi> of Money, by <hi>Intereſt, Procuration, Continuation,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">It is the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of ſome others, as well as my own, That all Maſters of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships ſhould be Taxed abroad, together with the Factors; for they are come now to act in half Commiſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the Factors. And, to ſpeak with all Modeſty, they gain above <hi>12 per Cent.</hi> more than the Merchants do, by more advantageous Trading.</note> And there are a great many concern'd in this Craft, that ſhould refund a great deal for the preſent Occaſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>And, if our Trade and Juſtice be regulated together with our Coin, and Religion honeſtly and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, our King's
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:37530:36"/>moſt excellent Majeſty may uſe a greater Style of Soveraignty than this of King <hi>Edgar,</hi> wherewith (and with a few other Words) I conclude:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ego Edgarus Anglorum</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>omnicumque Regum Inſularumque Oceani Britannici circumjacentium, cunctarumque Nationum quae infra eam includuntur, Imperator, ac Dominus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now (I think, from what hath been ſaid, or rather ſhewn) it may be ſeen a little, how much God and Nature have done for us, more than we endeavour to do for our ſelves. And I wiſh that any part of this Enterprize may anſwer the Ends for which the whole was deſign'd, with all Sincerity and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will.</p>
               <p>For elſe I would have robb'd and ſtollen from the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities I have acknowledged, tranſmigrated their <hi>Diſpenſat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> into the Wrong Appropriation, and, made thoſe <hi>Doctors Opinions</hi> paſs for my own, who am the moſt unfit Perſon to preſcribe any thing for the Diſtempers of State, in a Corrupted Time.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37530:36"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
